<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The vvorlds assises. Or A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the tenth day of Iuly 1614. being the Sunday before the end of Trinity terme. By Nathanael Kitchener, student in diuinitie, and preacher of Gods word at Grauenhurst in Bedfordshire</title>
            <author>Kitchener, Nathanael, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 55 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A72487</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14948</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123148</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99900260</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99900260</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150657</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A72487)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150657)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1966:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The vvorlds assises. Or A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the tenth day of Iuly 1614. being the Sunday before the end of Trinity terme. By Nathanael Kitchener, student in diuinitie, and preacher of Gods word at Grauenhurst in Bedfordshire</title>
                  <author>Kitchener, Nathanael, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 94, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Lionell Snowdon [in the shop of Ralph Blower], for Iohn Harison, at the golden Anchor in Paternoster rowe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Ralph Blower's name from STC addendum.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery, San Marino, California.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Judgment --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Judgment of God --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:1"/>
            <p>THE VVORLDS ASSISES.</p>
            <p>Or A Sermon Preached at Paules Croſſe the tenth day of Iuly 1614. being the Sunday before the end of Trinity Terme.</p>
            <p>By NATHANAEL KITCHENER, Student in Diuinitie, and Preacher of Gods word at Grauenhurſt in Bedfordſhire.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>Looke vp, and lift vp your heads for your Redemption draweth neers.</hi>
               </p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luk. 21.28.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Aug. ad Iulianum, Epiſt. iij.</bibl>
               <p>Tria ſunt in hoc mundo deteriora omni ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, Anima peecatoris in peccatis perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, quae nigrior eſt coruo; &amp; mali Angeli, qui eam rapiunt; &amp; infernus in quem inducitur: non exim ſunt deteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ora his tribus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Imprinted at London, by <hi>Lionell</hi> Snowdon, for <hi>Iohn Hariſon,</hi> at the golden Anchor in Paterno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-rowe. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABL LORD</hi> CHARLES Earle of Kent, Lord of Haſting, <hi>Weisforde and Ruthin, and his Maieſties Lieftenant of the Shire of Bedford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable there be two things, which make any great houſe truely Noble, Loue to God, Loyaltie to Prince, with the former, this great noble houſe of KENT is now inueſted: in the latter it euer continued ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner tainted; in both a ſucceſſion hopefull ſtill expected. Religion (which is better then that lot of inheritance, giuen by <hi>Iacob</hi> to his ſonne <hi>Ioſeph</hi>) hath in your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip bin ſo long a Reſident, that any good man, euen by popular report, might preſent an Orpha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in hope of ſuccour: much more my ſelfe who know ſo well, am ſo
<pb facs="tcp:150657:3"/>much bounden, and can ſo true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpeake that of you which the Spirit did of the Church of Theatyra; <hi>I know thy Loue, and Seruice, and Faith, and thy Patience, and thy Workes, and that they are moe at the last then at the firſt.</hi> I haue here expoſed myne Infant, (a formeleſſe Embrion) to the mercie of the Preſſe, and the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the mercileſneſſe of cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; the poore abortiue reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling <hi>Alcibyades</hi> childe, of whom the querulous mother made com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, <hi>That Nature begunne it, but did not compleatly finiſh it:</hi> ſhrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both vnder your worthy Patronage, as an <hi>Aiax</hi> buckler for defence. All is done in benefit of the Church wherein I liue, in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of dutie to your perſon, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I honour: to ſatisfie my friends whom I loue, and to content any good man, whom I like. Thus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
<pb facs="tcp:150657:3"/>the happineſſe of Heauen and Earth, to attend your ſoule and body. I beſeech him who made all, to adde much honour to your dayes, and many daies to your honourable life: In hope whereof, I take my humble leaue, and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips Chaplaine in all obſeruance.</hi> N: Kichener.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:4"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Eader, (if curteous, I muſt thanke, if capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, I can indure) there be two ſorts of beaſts whereof I warne my Youngling; moone-eyde Ignorance, and bleere-eyde Enuie; the one with <hi>Melitides</hi> cannot iudge at all, the other with <hi>Zoilous</hi> will iudge too much: the fathers councell is, That his child auoid both. But if the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellations be maleuolous, why yet the Poet ſaith, <hi>Scribimus indoctidoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique &amp;c.</hi> So ſome of thoſe cattell may prooue with young themſelues, and then others may doe as much for theirs. If happily at any time mine Oſpring be conuented before <hi>Felix,</hi> eares itching after newes; it anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth for it ſelfe, that of Salomon, <hi>Non eſt qnidquam noui ſub ſole.</hi> Far as the Comedian ſaid, <hi>Nihil eſt iam dictum, quod non ſit dictum prius.</hi> If it be taxed by ſoothing <hi>Zid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:150657:4"/>that with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> it weareth a parti-colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red coate, or that Iay-like it borroweth feathers from other birds; <hi>In promptu cauſa eſt.</hi> It pleads antiquity as the firſt Apoligie. It haue bin the ancient cuſtom euen of the learned ſo to do, <hi>Tum vt certiora ſcribant, tum vt iucundius legantur.</hi> Next it anſwereth for it ſelfe with Patricius, <hi>Me parum admodum fidei rebus meis adhibuiſſe, ſi ſolu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> authoritati meae in terarer.</hi> Thirdly it puts in that plea of <hi>Lipſius</hi> for his politicke Ceutons, in it owne behalfe, <hi>Nil noſtrum &amp; omnia:</hi> Only the kingly policie of <hi>Aſtyages</hi> is the fear of my young One, who vpon his dreame, married his only daughter to a poore ſhepheard, That the means of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther might derogate from the childs minde. In fine <hi>Cor: Agrippa</hi> ſaid, <hi>Inter Diuos nullos non carpit Momus;</hi> and how then ſhall Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals thinke to eſcape? Grauenhurſt. Octob, <hi>1615.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine if thou loue the Lord Ieſus. N: K.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="encomium">
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:5"/>
            <head>Vpon this Sermon touching the Iudgement of the World. Preached at <hi>Paules Croſſe,</hi> by <hi>N: K. Encomiaſticall Verſes, of</hi> A: W. <hi>in loue to the Author his eſpeciall friend, and his Booke a Iudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Worke.</hi>
            </head>
            <l>IN naught ſaue in Chriſts Croſſe <hi>Paul</hi> glory had,</l>
            <l>In naught more then Pauls Croſſe maey we be glad,</l>
            <l>Whereby men doe this Triple honour raiſe,</l>
            <l>
               <hi>God glory, this Land Good, &amp; Theirſelues praiſe.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>Amongſt the reſt, let me, Iudicious friend,</l>
            <l>Commend thy Booke, thy Booke ſhal thee commend,</l>
            <l>By thee, the Iudgement of the World's explain'd,</l>
            <l>Wherein a World of Iudgement is containd,</l>
            <l>Thy Iudgement of the Worlds Iudgement we ſee,</l>
            <l>Feare not the Iudgement of the World of thee.</l>
            <l>The Worlds Iudgement thy Booke ſo well diſplai's</l>
            <l>The Iudgement of thy Booke the World muſt praiſe.</l>
            <l>Thy Booke may mend the world by ſinnes detection,</l>
            <l>But the World cannot mend thy Booke's perfection.</l>
            <l>Both Booke and World ſhall ſurely once decay,</l>
            <l>But both ſhall laſt vnto the latter Day.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Ni fruſtra Augurium vani docuere parentes.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Wilbore, Ma. Art Syd. Coll. Cant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150657:5"/>
            <head>The VVorlds Aſsiſes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable, right Worſhipfull, worthy, and Chriſtian men, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, it is a receiued opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in <hi>Philoſophie,</hi> that the motion of the inſerior <hi>Orbe,</hi> is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned by the motion of the ſuperior. I may well compare this Chaire to a dimmy heauen, wherein the Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Orbe</hi> of our bleſſed <hi>Horizon</hi> doe often moue. I may like<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it to the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein the fixt ſtartes being ſet, doe twinckle and glitter, to the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of moſt. The <hi>Orbe</hi> wherein my ſelfe am carried, is one of the loweſt: yet now according to the will of God, the <hi>Primus motor,</hi> and my worthie friends that mooued, I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150657:6"/>am here in motion. In this my moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I deſire with the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to the king of <hi>Hesbon. Deut.</hi> 2.27. to paſſe along the high-way of my Text, turning neither to the right-hand, nor to the left: onely as <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iah</hi> ſaid to <hi>Ahabs</hi> meſſengers. 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.13. <hi>As the Lord liueth, what my God ſaith, that will I ſpeake.</hi> So ſay I, what my Text hath put into my hand, and the Lord ſhall put into my heart; the one will I touch, the other will I teach. It may be expected by ſome, that mine inferior Orbe ſhall bee carried accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the propper motion of the <hi>Primum Mobile;</hi> or that it ſhall imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the wonted motion of the Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Orbe; or ſith ſome ſay, its <hi>A na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura huius loci, The cuſtom of this place, to ſummon the manners of this citie:</hi> that therefore mine ſhall wade into thoſe abuſes, wherein it ſelfe is a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger: I anſwere, No it ſhall not. For min own part, I ſay with the Prophet. <hi>Puer ſum, neſcio loqui. ler.</hi> 1.6. <hi>I am a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger here,</hi> no traueller in the world: I know that <hi>Tortuoſae viae, Crooked, cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neld
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150657:6"/>waies;</hi> and <hi>Malimores, Bad and worſe conditions,</hi> are neerely allyed: yet how the kindred comes in, I deſire not to ſearch the Records, leaſt happily without deſire I might looſe my ſelfe. While I was muſing vnder the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then of my thoughts, what text to take that behooued many: this my text met me, offering it ſelfe to me and you, and it concernes all? It was at my choiſe to chooſe, and ſpeake what all know: but in my choiſe I chooſe, to ſpeake what the moſt know not. I might ſpeake to you reuerend Iudges, to take heed of peruerting iudgement: leaſt you euert your ſelues, when your ſelues ſhall come to iudgement: but I would faine ſuppoſe, that they who know equitie, will doe right. I might ſpeake to this Honourable wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Lord Maior, that he would be a father to the fatherleſſe, and defend the cauſe of the widow; that he would eleuate virtue, and debelitate vice: but I heare ſo much of you, that this hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatory ſpeech I heare will be needleſſe, notwitſtanding I heare that ſin ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150657:7"/>here, that vnleſſe the whippe ſcourg it, the ſcourge is like to whip al. I might ſpeake to the noble &amp; learned Clergie, my brethren; that they like <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> would be burning lights, and not like <hi>Demas</hi> burnt-out lights: but this they know as well as I, and I muſt ſtriue as well as they. I might ſpeake to the ſpeakers at the Law, that they with care would maintaine their Clients; as their Clients at coſt retaine them: but they are wiſe and know much, and in their wiſdome cannot but know this. I might ſpeake to the faſhion-mongers (men and women) of our age, that they would imbrace <hi>Pauls</hi> counſel. <hi>Rom</hi> 12.2. <hi>Not to faſhion them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues like vnto this world:</hi> but this hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beene a faſhion among many my predeceſſours heretofore, my ſelfe am willing to leaue this faſhion now: I might ſpeake to all with my Sauiour. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.14. and ſo I will and doe <hi>Sinne no more,</hi> becauſe each one muſt die and come to iudgement, <hi>All muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all to the Iudge of al.</hi> The <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher</hi> ſaith, <hi>Primus motor mouet primum
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150657:7"/>mobile, &amp; Primum mobile caetera omnia: the chiefe mouer moues the firſt mouable &amp; it all the reſt.</hi> Be God almighty the firſt mouer: ſuppoſe me for this time &amp; place the chief mouable, &amp; your ſelues my iudicious Auditors, the bodies to be moued. Meane while God grant my ſpirit of mediocritie, the voice of the Bird of Paradiſe, of whom I reade that ſhe moues all to repentance to whom ſhe ſings: which if I asking ſhal receiue I will think this a bleſſed time beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: in defire wherof, I craue your atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue hearts to that portion of ſcripture, which I finde thus written.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 17.31.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>He hath appointed a day in the which he wil iudge the world in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes, by that man whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>BLeſſed <hi>Paul</hi> who of a <hi>Peelar</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came a <hi>Pillar,</hi> of an earneſt perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuter. <hi>Act.</hi> 8. became a zealous Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. <hi>Act.</hi> 13. being guided by the ſpirit from citie to citie to preach, in the end he came to <hi>Athens,</hi> as appeares in this
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150657:8"/>17 chapter, verſ. 15. Where being, he was brought into the <hi>Streete of Mars.</hi> ver. 19. &amp; there paſsing along, he ſtood and told them what he had obſerued, An altar wherein was written, vnto the vnknowne God. verſ. 23. Whereupon <hi>Paul</hi> took occaſion to preach vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>The liuing God,</hi> declaring vnto them, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at he was the framer of this worlds Architecture that he dwelt not in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>made temples, that he is not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped with bandie workes. ver. 25. that he giues breath to all, and appointed to euery thing his ſeaſon: that in him we liue, and mooue, and haue our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, verſ. 28. and therefore that we, who liue, and mooue, and be, ſhould Repent, verſ. 30. Becauſe, as my text hath it in this verſe. 31. <hi>He hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a day in the which he will iudge the world in righteouſneſſe, by that man whom he hath appointed.</hi> In which words I note fiue things.</p>
            <p n="1">1.<note place="margin">Parts <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> The certainety of the day, ſet downe by a double <hi>Affidauit:</hi> firſt the Author, <hi>He,</hi> that is, <hi>God.</hi> 2. The reſclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Hath appointed.</hi> 2. The vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150657:8"/>of the day, in that it is not limited, coacted, or reſtrained to a day defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiue. This or that day, but to a day in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>definite, <hi>A day,</hi> The end of the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to <hi>Iudge the world.</hi> 4. The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, how, <hi>In righteouſneſſe.</hi> 5. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie who, <hi>By that man whom he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed.</hi> In ſpeaking of which words, I craue this ſole fauour, that all things may be taken, and not miſtaken as they are ſpoken.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the certaintie, The Power of God hath an appointed day for the cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>atio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, The great world the mercy of God had it appointed day in the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of man, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> The little world: now the iuſtice of God muſt haue the appointed day for the iuſt puniſhment of the vniuſt little world that ſoiourns in the great world, for <hi>Fundamenta,</hi> The foundations of the Continent ſhall be ſhaken, and then <hi>Blandamenta,</hi> The follies of the contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſhall be ouerthrowne. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaking of the certainety of this day, ſaith. <hi>The day of the Lord will come as a thiefe in the night, in the which the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150657:9"/>heauens ſhall paſſe away with a noiſe, the elements ſhall melt with heate, and the earth with the workes that are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in ſhall be burnt vp, and we muſt looke for new heauens, and new earth,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.10. For I doe beleeue that at the end of the world there ſhall goe a great and terrible fire either hard before, or with the comming of the Iudge. But now whether this fire ſhall be <hi>Elementum ignis, the element of fire in it owne proper ſphere,</hi> or whether all the fires on the earth, or in the earth among the ſtones and minerals, or whether ſuch a fire, <hi>Qualem excitabit tum deus, as the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall then raiſe:</hi> whether, I ſay, it ſhall be all of theſe <hi>Coniunctim</hi> in one or any of theſe <hi>Deuiſim</hi> ſeuered, that I know not And that fire ſhall conſume this world, it ſhall <hi>Corpora incinerare, terrae naſcentia abſumere, &amp; in nihilum redigere: burne bodies</hi> (not all) <hi>into aſhes, conſume all the vegetatiue things on the earth, and bring them to nothing.</hi> Alſo, I looke for new heauens and new earth, but how new? <hi>Quoad formam, non quoad ſubſtantiam: New in regard of the</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:150657:9"/>forme and faſhion: not new in reſpect of the matter and ſubſtance. In this I hold with <hi>Aug. Ciuit. lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lementa, id eſt, Caelum &amp; terram non eſſe abolenda, ſed in melius commutanda: figurem, id eſt imaginem mundi, non ſubſtantiam berituram.</hi> That is <hi>The E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements, heauen and earth ſhall not be taken quite away, but changed into bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: the faſhion,</hi> that is, <hi>the likeneſſe of the world ſhall periſh, but not the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance therrof.</hi> Iumping with this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Auguſtin</hi> is that of <hi>Saint Greg. Mor. lib.</hi> 17. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>Caelum &amp; terra per eam quam nunc habent imaginem tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeunt, ſed tamen per eſſentiam ſine fine ſubſiſtunt: caelum igitur &amp; terra &amp; tranſit &amp; erit; quoniam ab ea quam nunc habet ſpecie per ignem tergitur, &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men natura ſua ſeruatur,</hi> That is, <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth paſſe away through that Image which they now haue: but in their Being they remaine without end: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore beauen and earth ſhall both not bee, and be, becauſe from it now-ſhape it is ſcoured and made cleane by fire, but the nature and condition thereof</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150657:10"/>is ſtill continued; agreeing to that of <hi>Pſal.</hi> 101. <hi>Thou ſhalt change them &amp; they ſhall be changed.</hi> Now that this great &amp; dreadfull day will come, <hi>Pie credendum</hi> we muſt vndoubtedly and holily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue. The Prophet <hi>Malichi</hi> ſaith, <hi>The day of the Lord will come burning like an ouen. ca.</hi> 4.1. and it is a rule among the Schoolemen, <hi>Futurum in deo aeque cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum, quam aut preſens, aut praeteritum:</hi> Will, in God giue as much certaintie as Is the future tence is as ſure as the preſent tence, or preter-perfect tence: that which is to come in God, is as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as what is either preſent, or paſt. Therfore the Prophet <hi>Ioel</hi> (happily hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reference to this poſition) ſaith, <hi>The day of the Lord is come, for tis at hand c.</hi> 2.1. The Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> in the 13. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his Propheſie, and <hi>Abdi</hi> in his ſhort Propheſie, ſay both, <hi>It is at hand.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Zephaniah</hi> ſaith, <hi>It is hard by.</hi> Therefore there needes no doubt be made of the certaintie: neither is there any queſtion of the miſerie. <hi>Eſay</hi> cals it a day of trouble &amp; ruine. <hi>cap.</hi> 22. <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> cals it a day of vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. <hi>c.</hi> 46. <hi>Ioel</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:150657:10"/>cals it a fearfull day. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>Amos</hi> cals it a darke day. <hi>c</hi> 8. <hi>Zephoniah</hi> cals it a day of wrath. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Zephany</hi> cals it the ſpecial day <hi>c.</hi> 14. <hi>Bern.</hi> ſpeaking of the dreadfulnes of this day, ſaith, <hi>Plaugent Iudaei, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent gentiles, Plangent Chriſtiani, plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ones qui magis mundum amarunt quam deum, plangent ſuam culpam quam commiſerunt, ſuam ſtultitiaem quam nen corrererunt, ſuam gloriam quam amiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt, ſuam paenam quam incorrererunt.</hi> Iewes ſhall weepe, Gentiles ſhall weepe, Chriſtians ſhall weepe, all ſhall weepe that loued the world, more then God. They ſhall lament the faults they haue committed, their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie they haue not corrected, the glory that they haue loſt, and the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they haue incurred. And indeede well may they weepe, for aboue they ſhall ſee the angrie Iudge, whom they haue offended. Beneath, hell gaping which they haue deſerued; Without, the world burning which they haue delighted. Within, the conſcience ſtinging, which they haue ſurcharged. On the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150657:11"/>right hand their ſinnes accuſing which they haue commited: on the left hand, euill Angels tugging them; about them good Angels driuing them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hell. Therefore let me ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>What manner of men ought wee to be in holy conuerſation of life.</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>For the time is come that Iudgement muſt beginne at Gods houſe.</hi> If it beginne at vs firſt, what ſhall bee the end of them that obey not the Goſpell of God? <hi>And if the righteous ſcarce be ſaued, where ſhall the vngodly and ſinner appeare?</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 17. The firſt iudgement was in water, to coole the riotous heate of luſt, that then did abounde, when <hi>Bigamie</hi> and <hi>Polygamie</hi> was ſuffered: but the laſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſhall be in fire, to purge this away raining deſire of gold, and heate the lukewarme charitie, that now the world being old, waxeth cold Our Sauiour ſpeaking of the fearfulnes of this day, ſaieth. <hi>The Sun ſhal be dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, the Moon ſhal not giue her light, the Stars ſhal fall from heauen, the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken, all kindreds, of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150657:11"/>earth ſhall mourne, and ye ſhall ſee the ſonne of man comming in the clouds of heauen with power and great glory. Mat.</hi> 24.29. That is, the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bodies ſhall indure great alteration, to terrifie the wicked, and be Criers (as it were) vnto them, to ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon them before the great Tribunall. But how the ſunne ſhall be darkned, how the moone ſhall not giue her light, how the ſtars ſhall fall from heauen (which really cannot be) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the leaſt ſtarre is ſo much bigger then the whole earth) and how the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken: to ſay truth, we cannot now iuſtly deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine: let me therefore ſay with that worthy <hi>Aug. Ciuit. lib</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 30. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis tum docebit rerum experientia quam noſtra iam conſequi poſsit intelligentia, The experience of things which we ſhall ſee then ſhall teach vs better then we can conceiue now.</hi> But howſoeuer, it ſhall be terrible, yea ſo terrible, that as <hi>Aug:</hi> ſpak of God, <hi>Verius cogitatur deus quam dicitur, &amp; verior eſt quam cogitatur. God is truer thought of, then ſpoke of, and yet himſelfe much truer then both.</hi> So ſay
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150657:12"/>I of iudgements terror, it is ſooner i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magined then expreſſed, eaſier thought then ſpoken: and yet in it ſelfe more hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deous, then either imagined, expreſſed, ſpoke, or thought. <hi>Terribele eſt illud iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicium, in euitabilis paeua, intollerabile tormentum:</hi> It is a terrible iudgement, a paine ineuitable, a torment intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: but yet <hi>Quid ſit,</hi> Directly what one it is as <hi>Aug. Eucher. c.</hi> 38 ſaid of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſity of the Angels Potentiality: ſay I of this, <hi>Dicaut quipoſſint, dummodo qd. dicunt probare valeant,</hi> Let them ſpeak who can, ſo be what they ſpeake they can proue. This is and thus is the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d comming of Chriſt, &amp; this far different from that that was <hi>In humilitate,</hi> in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militic like a ſeruant, this ſhal be <hi>in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtate,</hi> in magiſtie like a king, that was <hi>in infirmitate</hi> in infirmitie like a ſheepe to the ſſaughter: this ſhall be <hi>in pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate,</hi> in power like a Lion to his prey, that was in pouerty, being <hi>Infans in praeſepio,</hi> an infant in a manger, this ſhal be in dignitie being <hi>Index in iudicio,</hi> A iudge to giue ſentence, that was in <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſericordia,</hi> in mercie to confirme al, this
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150657:12"/>ſhall be <hi>In iuſticia,</hi> In iuſtice to confou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d moſt: He was then <hi>Homo inter homines,</hi> a man amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is now <hi>Deus ſupra An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelos,</hi> A God aboue Angels: &amp; yet thogh a God, he will come like a man to iudge men &amp; wicked Angels: there was a time when he did <hi>Pati pro peccatis,</hi> ſuffer for our ſins, &amp; after a time ther wil be a time when yet there ſhall be no time, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhall with him as he doth now <hi>Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phare cum liberatis</hi> Triumph with freeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> freely freed; what time he wil ſeuer vs, <hi>A damnatis,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe whom his rigor hath appointed to be damned. I remember the Scriptur ſpeaks of <hi>Dauid,</hi> that he was wrath with <hi>Nabal</hi> for denying him victu als at his ſheepſhearing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was an hungred in his flight; &amp; ſo <hi>Abigaile</hi> was faine to appeaſe him.<note place="margin">1. Sam. 25.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus Chriſt ſhall come in flaming fire, to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vengea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that know him not, nor obey his Goſpell.<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 2.8</note> No <hi>Abigaile</hi> ſhall ſerue for interceſſion. The terror of that day ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be vttered, becauſe the iudges ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tence ſhall not be altered: ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> while he was liuing, would euer be ſinning: and God after that ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wil euer bepuniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150657:13"/>Then ſhall the Archangels loud voice be heard, that voice which cleaueth the rockes, openeth the graues, raiſeth the dead, oyneth ſoules to their bodies, &amp; all <hi>In momento, In a moment,</hi> &amp; twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eie. Then ſhall the vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers miſery come, then ſhall be the ſtrict examination, the narrow ſerch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and idle words accounting: then <hi>Exigetur e nobis me tempus impenſum quomedo fuit expenſum. We muſt giue ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all time allotted vs how we haue beſtowed it:</hi> For, <hi>Non eſt capillus de ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite, nec momentum de tempore de quo rationem non reddendum. There is not an haire of our heads, nor a moment of time, for which we muſt not be accountable?</hi> the reaſon is, <hi>Cuia qui pro frigida agnae dabit mercedem,</hi> Becuſe he who for a cup of colde water will giue a reward, <hi>Pro verbo oſioſo ſtatuit paenam,</hi> For an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle word hath allotted a puniſhmet. He that created time, &amp; was borne for vs in the fulnes of time; be aſſured, he will iudg vs for our <hi>notvſed,</hi> or <hi>abaſed</hi> time; the greatma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the world, &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the little world, both haue a time, and time will
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150657:13"/>come that the Great ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall haue an end, &amp; the little man, who hued in the great ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be iudgd at that end. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that end ſhal com, the ſecrets of al harts ſhall be diſcloſed; for as <hi>Muſculus</hi> on Geneſis ſaith about Sodoms deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; <hi>Quod noctu peccatur luce diurna pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitur, Sinne by night committed, by day ſhall be puniſhed.</hi> Then ſhall it be ſaide to a ſinner, as <hi>Nathan</hi> ſaid to <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.12.</note> 
               <hi>Thou didſt this ſecretly, but I will doe it before all Iſraell, and before the Sunne.</hi> In this world God afflicts his choſen, and then iudge how in the next world he will toment the wicked. And as <hi>Greg:</hi> ſpeaking of <hi>Herods</hi> cruelty to holy <hi>Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Magna crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lit as cum ſacram caput fuit decollatum, maior cum allatum &amp; homicidium oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatum, adhuc maior quia ſaltatrici da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ſed Maxima quia in poteſtatem ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ulterae aſſignatum, It was great crueltie to behead an holy man, more to bring the heade, and make boaſt of the murther, greater to giue it to a Dancer, but grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then all to aſsigne it into the hands of an Adultreſſe:</hi> In the end concluds it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150657:14"/>with this remarkable note; <hi>Hinc vnuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſq colligat quid illic paſsuri ſunt quos reprobat, ſi hic ua cruciat deusquos amat</hi> By this may aliſuppoſe how God will torture y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wicked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> next world who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hateth, when hee thus afflicteth his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in this world who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he loueth. In this world heads to his ſeruants falts.<note place="margin">Iob. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>In the world to come he wil ſift the vngod lies ſins.</hi> And as <hi>Bar: in Can. ſer.</hi> 15. ſaith, <hi>Quid in Babilone tutum ſi in Hieroſoly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma fiat ſcrutinum?</hi> If there bee made a ſerch in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, what ſafety can be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected for Babylon. The Papiſts ſay, if there be but two places, Heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; hel, &amp; <hi>Non eſt quis medius locus vt poſsit u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/> mo eſſe niſi cum Diabolo qui non eſt cum Chriſto.</hi> There is none interſtitial place but that he who is not with God muſt needs be with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> denil. If y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euery one (as the truth is.) after this life, is imediatly, <hi>In puncto temporis.</hi> In a very inſtant of time gone to ſoys or to pains, hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward or puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t; what then need we a Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day? I anſwer yes, in two re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpects. 1. Becauſe the body hath bin a coage<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Soule in good or in euil,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150657:14"/>&amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> body, as yet lyeth ſenceleſſe in the graue, &amp; ſhall ſo do vntil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> laſt dome, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without any feeling: now, it is meet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> as it hath bin a coactor, ſo it may be a copartner, that which vntil then it ſhal not be. 2 Becauſe God will render to euery one according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> full meaſure of Mercy, or Iuſtice; &amp; ſo it is that vntil that Iudgement day, neither the godly ſhal haue their ful fruition, &amp; conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of ioyes, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wicked of pains their meaſure: wherfore to make both co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pleat &amp; abſolute, ioyes to the godly, and pains to the wicked; As alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> two old friends might meet again together to renew old acquaintance. A Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day muſt be. Gods mercie was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, his ſon Ieſus miſuſed, therefore his iniuries muſt be reuenged, his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies muſt be confounded, the wicked muſt together be puniſhed; <hi>Vt tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis panalibus ſocientur qui ſocij fuerunt in vitijs.</hi> To aſſociate them in torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, who were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s in ſin. <hi>Paul</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third Pope of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> name made queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of three things liuing, which dying, he ſaid hee ſhould bee reſolued off. 1. <hi>In ſit Deus</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150657:15"/>if there were a God. 2. An <hi>Annimae im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortales, If ſoules did liue after the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies were dead.</hi> 3 <hi>Siqui inferno, If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny were in Hell?</hi> Now theſe three que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions will haue time after the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment-time to be diſcuſſed by leaſure: the one to the Athiſt, the other to the careleſſe Liuer; the laſt to the vnrepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant offender: all three to the ſayle of Hell, the damned perſons in Priſon.</p>
            <p>Now to this neceſſitie of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t generall, two things make a certaintie to euery man in perticular. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor. 2 The reſolution. 1 The author is God, and that God is, <hi>Ordo naturae, natura mentis humanae, terrores conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae, ordo ſocietatis Politicae, ſacrorum hominum coucenſus. The wonder full de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie euen of nature the nature of mans mind the terrors &amp; ſtings of conſcience, the order of politicall ſocietie betweene man and man doth plainly ſhew.</hi> As <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Armil. aurea.</hi> Nay, as the heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Orator ſaid; <hi>Nulla geus tam ſera, There is no Nation ſo wilde,</hi> no Harbarian ſo barbarous, but in heart will acknowledge it; Wherefore in his
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150657:15"/>
               <hi>Tuſc. Queſtions,</hi> he reports of <hi>Protago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras Abderites,</hi> that becauſe he beganne his booke with doubt, <hi>De dijs vero ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que vt ſint, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> vt non ſiut dicere habeo, As concerning the Gods, I haue nothing to ſay, but that they may be and may not be.</hi> He was baniſhed the citie, and the whole contry by a publike Edict, and with a generall conſent his bookes were burnt to aſhes. Now this God, that is, is <hi>Magnus ſine quantitate, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus ſine qualitate, Is great without quan titie, good without qualitie.</hi> As <hi>Aug.</hi> ſaith, Whoſe freewil elected vs, whoſe power created vs, whoſe loue preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs, whoſe mercie at the appointed day will crowne vs, if we in our allot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted dayes will ſerue him. This God is called in Latine <hi>Deus</hi> of <hi>Do, to giue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1.17.</note> becauſe, <hi>Onem dat, He giues euery good and perfect gift.</hi> In Engliſh he is called <hi>God, Quaſi good,</hi> yea he is goodneſſe it ſelfe, and no good thing will hee keepe from them that feare him, and ſerue him in holineſſe and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of life. This Iudgement day then, is good, in reſpect of God and man; In
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150657:16"/>God, to ſhew his great mercy &amp; iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to the godly &amp; the wicked: In man, that a crowne immortal might be abſolute, that the fulnes of perfec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might make a perfect fulnes. 2 The reſolution, he not only in a kind of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentionall determination verbally ſaid it, that which had bin ſufficient too, for,<note place="margin">Pſal. 33.9.</note> 
               <hi>Dixit &amp; factum eſt.</hi> He ſpake the word and it came to paſſe. But more, he hath with mature deliberation re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued vpon it: for my Text ſaith: <hi>Hee hath appointed a day:</hi> that is, Flatly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed vpon: As if the bleſſed Trinity had held a Councel about it, as about the making of man. <hi>Let vs make man.</hi> So,<note place="margin">Gen. 1.26.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs apoint a day for Iudgement.</hi> And then after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſecret heauenly Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hold, the Act was publiſhed (as a reuealed thing which belongs to vs &amp; our children for euer.) <hi>That there is an appointed day of Iudgement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> Agreeing to this is that of the <hi>He. c.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Statu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt hominibus vt ſemel moriantur, paſtea vero iudicium.</hi> It is apointed for all men once to die, and after that coms the Iudgement. It is appointed, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore needs muſt be; nay both apointed,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150657:16"/>&amp; therfore ſhal be, <hi>Death</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudgement</hi> too. With god is no cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge no alterati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, no ſhadow of either: for, <hi>Ego domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus &amp; non mutor.</hi> I am the Lord and I cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge not,<note place="margin">Mal. 3, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Solus deus recipit immortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, quia non capit mutalit atem.</hi> Only god is imortal becauſe only God is i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutable. <hi>The heauens change &amp; look old as doth a garment but thouart the ſame &amp; thy years fail not.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſa. 102.27.</note> Why doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſun guid y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moon &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtars gouern y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night? Becauſe god hath apointed it. why doth not the ſea ouerflow the earth, it being ſo many degrees higher, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, but keep it ſelfe in it bounds which it paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth not? Becauſe God appointed it. Why haue we a winter &amp; a Summer? and not al one ſeaſon of the yere? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath appointed it. Why doe al the godly look for a iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t day? Becauſe god hath appointed it. So we haue light and darknes, day &amp; a night, a ſpring &amp; a fal. Al becauſe god apoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all. If your aske me, why <hi>Iacob</hi> was predeſtinat before al worlds to ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; <hi>Eſaw</hi> hated to damnation? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer <hi>Statuitdeus,</hi> becauſe god apointed. If you aske me why <hi>Saul</hi> was caſheird
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150657:17"/>of his Kingdome, and <hi>Dauid</hi> inthro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned? I anſwere, <hi>Statuit Deus, God hath appointed it.</hi> If you aske me, why <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolon</hi> did hang betweene heauen and earth by the ruffinly hair of his head? (A deſtruction to giue our now ſuch people inſtruction,) I anſwere, <hi>Statuit Deus, God had appointed it.</hi> If you aske me, why I doe, and you muſt looke for a Iudgement day? I anſwere with my Text. <hi>Quia ſtatuit Deus, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God hath appointed it.</hi> The Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow hath many colours, two Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Fiery and Watry, the watry co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour remembreth vs of the Deluge paſt, and bids vs feare it no more: the Fiery aduertiſeth vs of the Iudgement to come, and bids vs daily looke for it. If you aske me why? I haue retained my Text, and what that ſpeakes is law, <hi>Statuit Deus Becauſe God hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 The ſecond part of my Text, is the vncertaintie of the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for, <hi>Quinatus ante tempus, Hee that was borne before time.</hi> And <hi>Qui dedit eſſe tempori, Who gaue a beeing to</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150657:17"/>all time, will come, <hi>In tempore,</hi> In a fit time; to iudge vs. <hi>Pro tempore,</hi> For loſt time, we who are Heires of time, when as <hi>Non erit amplius tempus,</hi> There ſhal be no more time. Time it ſelfe ſhal be no more, as wee read. <hi>Apock.</hi> 10.6. that is, <hi>No more time of perſecution, of mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of Sinne:</hi> whereof the ſixt Angel ſpake. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.13. <hi>The time of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at that time ſhall ceaſe, and yet time it ſelfe ſhall not haue ceſſation.</hi> Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt with all Complices of his ſhalbe deſtroyed, ſo there ſhall bee no time for hurt, nor deſtruction, ſith the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyer himſelfe ſhall bee deſtroyed: but, <hi>Ipſum Tempus in quantum tempus,</hi> Time in that it is time ſhall ſuffer no deſtruction. In three things appeares the vncertainety of the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. 1 The place where. 2 The manner how. 3 The time when. It is vncertaine in what place wee ſhall bee iudged. It is vncertaine in what manner wee ſhall bee Iudged, and it is vncertaine what time the Iudge will come to Iudgement. 1 The place, any particular place of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150657:18"/>or where the Iudge will appeare to Iudge, is to vs vtterly vnknowne; more then that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of. 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.17. <hi>Then wee who liue and remaine, ſhall bee caught vp in the clouds to meet the Lord in the Aire, and ſo ſhall bee with him for euer:</hi> So that the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall place is the Aire. In the 6. of <hi>Mat.</hi> 64. In the 13. of <hi>Marke</hi> 26. In the 21. of <hi>Luke</hi> 27. The Iudge there ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of himſelfe at his comming, ſaith; <hi>That it ſhall bee in the Clouldes of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> That is, both as the Marginall hath it, and as the moſt vnderſtand it. Sitting vpon the Clouds, as he was taken vp: which opinion is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon receiued opinion of the learned. There were of the Friers, and are at this day, of opinion, that the valley <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> which is ſituate towards the Eeaſt, betweene Ieruſalem and the Mount of Oliuet, ſhall bee the place where (ſay they) the throne ſhall bee ſet, and where wee ſhall all be Iudged: the proofe of which opinion, they cite out of <hi>Ioel.</hi> 2. <hi>chap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſe</hi> 2. where the text ſaith, <hi>I will gather all
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150657:18"/>nations, and will bring them downe into the valey Iehoſaphat.</hi> The reaſons mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them to this opinion are two. 1 Becauſe they hold Ieruſalem and the places about it adiacent, to bee neere the middle of the earth; and therfore being a place ſo copious, ſo famous, moſt fit for the place of Iudgement. 2 Becauſe <hi>Iohoſaphat</hi> in the Original, doth ſingnifie the Iudgement of the Lord. The which opinion of theirs, thus I anſwere. That for the places ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation to be about the middeſt of the earth or world, that I leaue to the Coſmographers to be decided, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their iudgement in that Arte and facultie. Alſo the wordes ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſication, ſhall cauſe none alteration; ſith they who are learned in the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe tongue, will acknowledge no leſſe.</p>
            <p>But for the places quotation, they muſt obſerue, that the Text is to bee vnderſtoode, either by way of alluſion, alluding to the valley where God did by a great and vnſuppoſed, vnexpected mean at the humble paier
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150657:19"/>of <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ouercome that good Kings enemies: for the enemies fell to Ciuill war among themſelues, and one ſlew another: <hi>Moab</hi> and <hi>Amon</hi> fell vpon Mount Seir, and they euery one vpon the other, as wee read 2. <hi>Cr.</hi> 20.23. And ſo this may haue a refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to that, and may fignifie the valley of deſtruction for the wicked. Or elſe doubtleſſe it hath relation vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the word <hi>Iehoſaphat,</hi> which ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Iudgement, or pleading, or arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating of matters. Wherfore I auerre concluſiuely, that it is not to bee vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the locall place of <hi>Iehoſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi> but onely of <hi>Iehoſaphat</hi> ſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and called, becauſe the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment then executed on the damned, ſhall reſemble that which was vpon <hi>Ichoſaphats</hi> enemies. Thus then of the place of Iudgement, no man muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, becauſe the Scripture doth no where define: for it is a Canon, Where the Scripture leaues none eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, wee muſt lend no faith: but that there ſhall bee a place, we muſt all reſolue; <hi>Latet dies &amp; locus, &amp; timea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150657:19"/>omnis dies &amp; locus, the day and place is vnkuowue, that euery day and</hi> (happily) <hi>Place too might bee feared.</hi> 2 <hi>The manner,</hi> the manner may partly bee geſſed, becauſe in holy writ it is plainly deſcribed. Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Videbunt in quempupugerunt, They ſhal ſee him whom they, thruſt through, cap.</hi> 19.37, <hi>Ergo ait Aug. vidibunt corpus ipſum quod lancea percuſſerunt, &amp; ſic videbitur, a pijs &amp; impijs, a Iuſtis &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtis, a gaudentibus &amp; plangentibus, a conficis &amp; confuſis. Therefore</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtine, They ſhall ſee that very bodie which they peareed with a Speare:</hi> and ſo he ſhalbe ſeene of the godly and the wicked, of the iuſt and the vniuſt, of them that ſhall reioyce and thoſe that ſhall lament, of thoſe that bee ſaued and thoſe that be confounded. The circumſtances then of the manner of the Iudges comming partly ſhall bee theſe fiue. 1 The Iudge ſhall Iudge in the meere forme of a man; yet not in the forme of a meere man, ſith he is, was, and will bee more then man. <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet homo verus, non tamen homo merus.</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:150657:20"/>this is plaine. <hi>Act.</hi> 1.2. Where when bee was taken vp into the Cloudes from his Apoſtles, as they ſtood loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſtedfaſtly towards Heauen, as he went; the Text ſaith, <hi>Two men ſtoode by them in white apparell,</hi> which ſaid, <hi>Yee men of Galile, why ſtand yee gazing into Heauen? This Ieſus which is taken vp from you into Heauen ſhal ſo come as ye bane ſeen him go into heauen.</hi> So, like a man he went, and like a man he ſhall come. <hi>Vnde Aug. Ser.</hi> 64 <hi>De verbis De; Forma illa erit Iudex quae ſub iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die eſtetit, illa iudicabit quae iudicata eſt.</hi> That forme ſhall bee Iudge that yeelded to a Iudge; that ſhall iudge, which was iudged it ſelf. And if iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be onely among the iuſt and holy Ones, to them would the Iudge appeare as in the forme of God, (ſayth this Docter) but becauſe all muſt bee iudged, iuſt and vniuſt, and ſith it cannot bee that the vniuſt and wicked ſhould ſee God. <hi>Talis appare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, Iudex qualis videri poſsit &amp; abijs quos Coronaturus eſt, &amp; abijs qua damnaturus eſt. Tract. in Iohn cap.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:150657:20"/>5 The Iudge ſhall ſo ſhewe himſelfe as hee may bee ſeene, both of thoſe that ſhall bee crowned, and thoſe which ſhall bee damned. For at that time he will, <hi>Dare praemia ſecundum bona opera, non propter bona opera. Giue rewards according to good works, but not for good workes;</hi> As may bee prooued. <hi>Apocal.</hi> 20. And <hi>Matthew</hi> 16.27. Alſo <hi>Ciuit. lib.</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 24. <hi>Manifeſtus veniet inter iuſtos &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtos indicaturus iuſte, qui prius ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit occultus ab iuiuſtis iudicandus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſte:</hi> Hee ſhall manifeſtly come among the both iuſt and vniuſt, to iudge iuſtly; who before obſcurely hidden, came among the vniuſt to be iudged vniuſtly.</p>
            <p>In the forme of a Seruant ſhall the Iudge bee ſeeene. <hi>Occulta erit forma Dei, Occultus erit in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uo Filius Dei, Hidden ſhall bee the forme of God, and the Sonne of God in thee forme of Man.</hi> The Sonne of man ſhall appeare, becauſe the power of GOD ſhall make that appearance: and the Sonne of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150657:21"/>God ſhal Iudge the appearers, becauſe hee will take the forme of man for the Iudgement. 2 <hi>Canet tuba, The Trumpe ſhall blow,</hi> that is, ſome admirable ſigne <hi>Accipitar, Shall bee receiued;</hi> which by diuine appointment, <hi>Dabitur, Shall be ginen:</hi> and this ſigne is diuerſly termed in the Scripture: Sometimes to bee <hi>The voice of an Archangell:</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times <hi>The trumpet of God:</hi> ſometimes <hi>The voice of the Sonne of God.</hi> And verily, it may well bee called a Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, becauſe God doth come then like one who is ready to wage warre againſt his enemies: and ſuch ſhall bee the virtue of it, that at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring thereof all ſhall ariſe. Though ſome, with the Martyres, haue their bones burnt to aſhes; others deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by beaſts, ſome rotted in the graue, ſome loſt in the earth, and one perhaps a thouſand miles from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: yet theſe all by Gods diuine power and might, ſhall bee vnited and knit together; and beeing the felſe ſame bones which the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had before it dyed, ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150657:21"/>the very ſame fleſh, though it be denoured by wormes, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to duſt from whence it came. Yea, and that <hi>Eaendem numero,</hi> the ſame nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merarie fleſh, as the Logitians terme it; and not <hi>Specie</hi> in ſhape and likeneſſe, as the Anabaptiſts falſely holde: <hi>Deum noua creare corpora: ſed his ſimilia,</hi> That God will create new bodies, but yet like to our former. In the 1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.6. it is ſaid, <hi>The Lord ſhall deſcend from heae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with a ſhout, with the voice of an Archangell,</hi> with the trumpet of God. A ſhout doth properly belong to mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners, who for incouragement doe al ſhout together when they caſt forth their oares: and it ſhould ſeeme the Apoſtle alludeth to theſe, both as the marginall note hath it, and as <hi>Aretius</hi> on that place expounds it. The ſame <hi>Aretius</hi> holds, the ſhoute to bee the loud crie of the Angels: <hi>Lyra</hi> &amp; <hi>Wirth,</hi> expounds this ſhoute, to be the crie of the Iudge calling all to iudgement: o-others thinke it ſhall bee the confuſed crie of all the vnreaſonable creatures. The voice of the Archangel, is thought
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:150657:22"/>by ſome to be The great and generall noiſe of the heauenly troupe, that ſhall attend the Iudge. <hi>Bucer</hi> thinkes it the hie note of the Captain of the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Hoaſt: <hi>Lyra</hi> ſaith, The voice of Chriſt, commanding all to iudgement, ſhall be <hi>vox imperatiua,</hi> the ſwaying, ouercomming voice, the voice of the Archangell calling to iudgement, ſhall be <hi>vox executiua,</hi> The accompliſhing or ſiniſhing voice, the voice of exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: that as the Saints ſhall iudge the world. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2: ſo when the Lord ſhall crie, <hi>Ariſe ye dead to iudgement,</hi> euen that crie ſhall be the Eccho, (as it were) and crie of the angelicall mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude. The trumpet of God, ſaith the Gloſſe, ſhall be the commanding all to ariſe. after which riſing, inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhall bee the iudgement. Others thinke, the trumpet ſhall be the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt appearing of the Iudge. <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> thinkes, it ſhall bee ſome out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſigne which may bee called and termed A Crie terrible and horrible, cauſing aſtoniſhment. But in this ſcrupuloſitie no mortall weight
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150657:22"/>can be a true Arbitrator: let mee therefore ſay with <hi>Aug. Hoc eſt in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilio dei: This is in Gods counſell.</hi> This wee know, that when the Law was giuen to the Iſraelites vpon mount <hi>Synai,</hi> The mount ſmoakt and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and a trumpit blew. <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.18. all was to mooue terrour and feare: and this beleeue, the trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet at the laſt day ſhall dreadfully blow, to terrifie the wicked, and comfort the godly, as alſo <hi>Aretius</hi> holdes. A trumpet is an inſtrument of vocalitie, properly vſed in warre, and by the call of a Trumpet (not a materiall one, dimentionate) ſhall we bee called to iudgement: what time, God will goe to battle with his enemies, and the fielde be yee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into his hands. Thirdly, The dead ſhall ariſe, the liuing ſhall bee changed; which change ſhall bee in ſtead of death. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51. Fourthly, <hi>The Angels ſhaell gather together the elect from the four Winds:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.31.</note> that is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the foure quarters of the world.Fiftly, The Stars ſhal be dark, either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> indeed &amp; truly,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150657:23"/>the Son was at the paſſion of our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, when <hi>Ferre non poterat creatura videre iniuriam creatoris.</hi> The creature was aſhamed to ſee the iniurie offered to the creator, and ſo bluſht for ſhame or els <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by reaſon of a great light then comming. Theſe are the maine circumſtances of that great mans man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of comming: among great men euery where ſo meanely conſidered. The Romans had a cuſtome, that when any offender was conuicted, they would put into the number or their names the double number of letters, the letters were A and C. and theſe were put <hi>In vrnam,</hi> into ſome holloe thing. A was the letter of abſolution, and if the offender drew that Lot, it was a Superſideas, he had his pardon, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding both his ofience and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence giuen on him. C. was the letter of condemnation, and if the poore pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner drew that; then the ſillie querdon was to prepare himſelfe for execution: for then, <hi>a Tamberlins,</hi> blacke tent was vp, nothing to be expected but deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. But alas, no ſuch A. ſhall be at
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150657:23"/>Doomes day; when a ſinner without a Sauiour, ſhall miſſe the <hi>venite. Mat.</hi> 25, 34. and the too late repentant, ſhal will he, nil he, draw the blacke C. of a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable He, againſt which time, God make vs all prouided. 3. <hi>The time,</hi> the time is to vs meerely vncertaine, <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium patefecit tempus celare voluit:</hi> He hath made known the manner, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiled the time. <hi>Aug. Epiſt. ad Heſenchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> ſaith. <hi>There are, Lord, which ſay they can make a computation of thy comming,</hi> but yet, of the very day and houre, (whereof my Sauiour ſpeaks. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24, <hi>De die autem &amp; horae illa nemo nouit, Of that day and houre, knoweth no man,</hi>) They ſay indeede they can giue no geſſe at all: for mine owne part, I ſay nothing but this, <hi>Id me velle ſcire, quod Chriſt us ait neminem ſcire poſſe,</hi> I would bee glad to know that, which Chriſt ſaith none can know at all. Wherefore the ſame father in another place giues this good counſell, That we ſhould not be like the idle ſeruant to ſay <hi>Moram faciet dominus meus, My Lord will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre his comming. Luk.</hi> 12.45. and ſo
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150657:24"/>beginne to eate and drinke with the dunken; nor yet reſemble the Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians. 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. To giue credit to euerie falſe report and tale, as if the day was now in being: but to watch carefully, as if it were <hi>In tergo,</hi> at hand, and at our very backes behinde vs; conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding thus, <hi>Nos itaque quod dominus ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re noluit, libenter neſciamus.</hi> Let vs reſt in willing ignorance, where the Lord would haue vs be in <hi>Neſcience,</hi> and be content not to vnderſtand, what God would haue no man to know. But as in the rules of Phiſicke, a diſeaſe is geſſed by the Symptomes, ſo in this great ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of heauen we may aime at it a lofe off, and deeme it to be nigh: but yet cannot tell, being aided onely by the Signes, to diuine when. <hi>Iohn Bap.</hi> was a <hi>Prodromus,</hi> a forerunner of our Sauiour &amp; preacht repentance. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.2. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, So there be certaine ſignes which are <hi>Prodromi,</hi> Preparers of the way, &amp; bring tidings of Iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts comming; which teach vs that leſſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Sauiour; <hi>Be ye therfore ready,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 24, 44</note> 
               <hi>for in ſuch an houre as you think not, wil the ſon of man come.</hi> Now
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150657:24"/>among theſe ſignes, I note three ſorts. 1. Some going lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of iugd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, of which ſort are theſe. Firſt, The preaching of the Goſpel throughout al the world among al natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. 2.<note place="margin">Mat. 24, 14.</note> The great ſecuritie &amp; gluttony, as was in the daies of <hi>Noah.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 24.38.</note> Such did go before the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of water, and ſuch ſhall go before the iudgement of fire, 3. The perelous times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall depart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith, &amp; giue heed to ſpirits of errour, &amp; do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of diuels. 4.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> The diſaſtrous diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in mens conuerſation, Pride, coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſnes, curſing, diſobedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, truce brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, with a bedroule more reckoned vp by <hi>Paul.</hi> 5.<note place="margin">2. Tim. 3, 1</note> The diſcloſing of the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an of ſinne, Antichriſt, the Popiſh ſonne of perdition. 6.<note place="margin">2. Theſ. 2, 3</note> The perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of the godly, the Church when men ſhall thinke they doe God good ſeruince in killing them. <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.2. Whereupon the Poet ſaith, <hi>Sanguine fundata eſt eccleſia ſanguine ſaepit: ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine ſuccreuit, ſanguine fiuis erit,</hi> The foundation, beginning, increaſe of the Church was with blood, &amp; with blood ſhall the end be. 7. Charity ſhal be cold,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150657:25"/>
               <hi>And the loue of many ſhall abate. Mat.</hi> 24.12. which thing being but ſeriouſly thought on, who would not thinke, but either wee liued vnder the frozen Zone, or that there was a continuall winter, in mens hearts. Secondly, there are ſignes going hard before the day of iudgement, as firſt, The Ecclipſes of the Sunne and Moone, both darkned ſcarce yeelding light. <hi>Mar.</hi> 13.24. wher in I ſay with <hi>Hemingius</hi> in his <hi>Syntag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, Quicquid accidit,</hi> Whatſoeuer coms to paſſe though a naturaliſt may giue a reaſon thereof; yet if it be extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary, as Ecclipſes, Inundations, Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, and the like, it is <hi>Portentum,</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doometh ſome thing. Secondly, The falling of the Stars, which is ment not really, but ſuppoſedly, as men ſhall i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine: meaning that al creatures ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally and ioyntly, ſhall bee <hi>Praecones,</hi> Cryars to ſummon vs before that hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid ſeate of iudgement. Thirdly, In the earth ſhall bee tumultuous qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king, on the earth nation ſhall riſe vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt nation, about the earth ſtrange rumours of warres, plagues, diſeaſes, fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150657:25"/>perſecutions. <hi>Luk.</hi> 21.10. In the Sea ſtrange breakings out and the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowings, that which our late wofull experience can too truely teſtifie. In the Aire dreadfull ſights, as were ouer Ieruſalem vpon her imminent deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, whereof <hi>Ioſephus</hi> writes. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, The calling of the Iewes, which <hi>Paulo</hi> prooues by three reaſons that it ſhall be. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. but how ſoone, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone knowes that knowes all. Thirdly, There are ſignes going with the day of iudgement. 1. The ſigne of the Son of man. 2. The lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tations of the Sons of men, <hi>All kindreds of the earth ſhall mourne, then ſhaell the Sonne of man come to indge, and the Angels bee ſent out to gather. Mat,</hi> 24.30. It is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among writers, what this Signe of the Sonne of man ſhall bee. <hi>Caluin</hi> ſeemes to holde it to be the glorie, and maieſty, and power of Chriſt, giuing notice as it were of his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming. <hi>Vt caele ſti potentiae praeditus, quae ſi ſigne in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime erecte, ad ſe conuertat totius muldi intuitum.</hi> That being furniſhed with heauenly power hee might ſet the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150657:26"/>whole world a looking at him, as it were with an elected ſigne on high. Many hold it to be the very body of Chriſt, retaining the wounds of his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, in his hands, feete, &amp; ſide; as <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culus</hi> cites the opinion. <hi>Theophilact</hi> on the 24 of <hi>Mathew,</hi> holds this ſigne, to be the ſigne of the Croſſe. <hi>Qua appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rebit in caelo ſuprae ſolem fulgens adargu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endos Iudaeos:</hi> which ſhal appeare in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhining aboue the ſunne to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the Iewes and be a Trophe, and kingly Enſine. This is likewiſe the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of <hi>Chryſoſtome Hom.</hi> 77. on <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew. Signum filij hominis erit ſignum Crucis, (non crux lignea in quam paſſus dominus, ſed Lux in dominum Crucis) ſole ſplendidiori:</hi> The ſigne of the ſonne of man ſhall be the ſigne of the Croſſe, brighter then the Sunne: for the Sunne ſhall be dakened, but the croſſe ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to abaſh the impndencie of the wicked, ſaith this golden mouthed father. <hi>Hier.</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. ſaith, We vnderſtand the ſigne of the croſſe, by the ſigne of the Sonne of man, that the Iewes may ſee him whom they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150657:26"/>thruſt through: as <hi>Zachar.</hi> ſpeakes. <hi>cap.</hi> 12.10. A worthy writer hath this compariſon, As a king entring 2 citie, goes before the armie, and hath his Banners and <hi>Vexilla regalia,</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly flagges carried before him: So the Lord of heauen, the King of kings, deſcending from the heauen of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uens, doth goe before his hoaſt of Angels, and Archangels; who car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying before the ſigne of the Croſſe, as a ſtandard of triumph: will relate to wretched men the comming of the heauenly King on earth to iudge the world. Now among thoſe perourſarie ſignes, they are all expired but theſe two, <hi>The preaching of the Goſpel throgh out all the world. Mat.</hi> 24. <hi>And the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the Iewes Rom.</hi> 2. throughout the whole chap. 1 As for the preaching of the Goſpell, if by all the world is ment (by the figure Sinecdoche) the moſt parts of the world; or the Iewes &amp; Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, the whole world being into them two deuided, as <hi>Maiſter Caluin</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands it: then is the ſignealſo expired, as hee auerreth; for ſo it hath beene.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150657:27"/>2. And for the calling of the Iewes though as yet it is not, (for there muſt not be a calling peculiar of one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular, Iew, or a few Iewes, but a generall calling of them all) neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe how ſoone it ſhall bee Man knoweth not: but that (they being in number ſo many, in places ſo diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, in religion ſo backward) as yet they are not, all doe graunt. Howſoeuer theſe ſignes being in a manner all ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled; they rubbe our dull memorie of the end of all things at hand, to be expected. <hi>Saint Hier.</hi> citeth 15 ſignes out of the olde Rabbins that ſhould goe hard before the day of iudgement, all which <hi>Scholaſt. Hiſt.</hi> ſaith that <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> found in the <hi>Annalibus libris He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breorum:</hi> &amp; theſe ſignes in number 15. are to be expired in 15 daies before the worldslaſt expiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; the breathing out the laſt gaſpe of the laſt day. 1. The firſt day, the Sea ſhall raiſe it ſelfe 40 cupits higher then the mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tains, ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding like a wall in it own place. 2. The ſeond day it ſhal ſo much go again into it ſelf, that it ſhall ſcarce be ſeene. 3. The 3 day, the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150657:27"/>habitants of the Sea, fiſhes ſhall appeare aboue the waters bellowing out, roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring and crying euen to hearten. 4. The fourth day, the ſea and all waters ſhall burne, 5 The fifth day, the trees &amp; herbs ſhall haue a bloody deawe. 6. The ſixth day, All edifices, and buildings ſhal fall. 7. The ſeuenth day, there ſhall be a generall rupture of the rocks in peeces 8. The eight day, the whole earth ſhall quake. 9. The ninth day, the ground ſhall be made plaine and leuell. 10. The tenth day, men ſhall goe out of caues and dens of the earth like mad men, &amp; not able to ſpeake one to another. 11. The eleauenth day, the bones of the dead ſhal ariſe, and be ouer their graues. 12. The twelfth day, the Stars ſhal fall from heauen, to the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of many 13. The thirteenth day, the liuing men ſhal die, that they may riſe with y dead. 14. The fourteenth day, heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth ſhall burn. 15. The fifteenth day, there ſhall be a new heauė, &amp; new earth, &amp; all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal ariſe. I quote not theſe as thogh I did, or would haue you beleeue thoſe <hi>Rabbins</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom <hi>Hier.</hi> made this rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150657:28"/>both becauſe the 13. is falſe, as alſo becauſe we haue Scripture for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie but of ſome of them, and for the order of none of them: Only to tel you that no Adamantine ſtony hart, can but tremble at the conſideration of theſe things &amp; to teachyou with care &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to prepare againſt the enſuing time of death &amp; iudgement: for it you be ready againſt death comes, you ſhall be happie when iudgement comes. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery mans deaths day is his particular iudgement day, &amp; <hi>Quocunque ceciderit arbor ibi erit Eccleſ.</hi> 2.3. As the tree fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſo it lieth: mankind reſembleth crecs ſome cut downe in their ſpring, ſome in their full grouth, ſome when they are dead. So is man, ſome die in youth, ſome in middle age, ſome in old age: and as the Axe, death, cuts downe the tree. Man, as the tree falleth, ſo it li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: as death doth leane vs ſo ſhal iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment find vs, &amp; as iudgement finds vs ſo ſhall ſentence paſle vpon vs. <hi>Qualis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieris ex hac vita, talis redderis futurae,</hi> Such as a man goes out of this life, ſuch ſhall he become at the future life. God
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150657:28"/>hath hidden fromvs this time of the laſt iudgement in diuerſe reſpects, 1. To try our faith and pacience, to poſſeſſe our ſoules therwith. <hi>Lu.</hi> 21.19. <hi>vincit quipae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titur.</hi> 2. To haue vs euer ready. 3. That the wicked might be without excuſe.<note place="margin">Mat, 24, 44</note>4.<note place="margin">Rom. 2.5</note> To bridle curioſitie not to ſearch into ſecret things which belong ro the Lord our God. In the 1.<note place="margin">Deut. 29, 29</note> of the <hi>Acts</hi> and 7 <hi>ve.</hi> the diſciples were tolde, It was not for them to know the times and ſeaſons, which the father hath put into his own power: &amp; if we growinquiſitiue, <hi>Moſes</hi> tels vs, <hi>The things reucaled belong to vs.</hi> Our Sauiour himſel ſpeaking of the iudgement day, ſaith;<note place="margin">Mat. 24.</note> 
               <hi>But of that day &amp; houre know eth no man, no not the Angels of heauen, ſaue the father only:</hi> what then needs man grieue to be ignorant, when the bleſſed Angels are content not to know it? yea more, Ieſus the Sonne of God, was content to be <hi>neſcient</hi> for our ſakes; <hi>In quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum homo,</hi> in that he was man. Some ſay, he knew it, euen <hi>Quatenus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo,</hi> as he was Man: but not <hi>Eatenus,</hi> to reueale it to men. Some haue
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150657:29"/>boaſted of reuelations, &amp; by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſet down deſinitiuely a certain day of iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſome by the Aſtrological aſpects of ſtars: ſome by Arithmetical ſupputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of numbers would diuine the time of the laſt time, &amp; al ſalſe, to ſeduce the ſimple. Of which ſorts of people, I may ſay as <hi>Cato</hi> ſaid of the Sooth-ſayers of his time: I wonder that they doe not laugh, when they meete each other in the ſtreets. There were diuerſe of the learned in times paſt; who held that as the wals in Iericho fell down the feue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th day after they were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſled about with blowing of tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets, &amp; ſhouting of the children of Iſrael, as we read. <hi>Ioſ</hi> 6.20. So the balding of this world, after thoſe 6 great daies wherof one is to the Lord as a 1000.<note place="margin">Pet. 3.8</note> years, &amp; a 1000. years as one day, ſhal fal: &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal be that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall ſabaoth, when al times &amp; ſeaſons ſhall meete together in coniunction, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſpeakes. <hi>ca.</hi> 66.23. Theold (Thadalmoſt ſaid the idle Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Elias</hi> falſly ſhrouded vnder his name in the Iewes Thalmuld) is much toſſed &amp; haled by many that the world
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150657:29"/>ſhal laſt 6000. years, 2000. <hi>vacui</hi> before the Law, 2000: vnder the Law, and 2000. vnder the Goſpel. The ſtrength of their weake coniecture is. 1 As in ſixe dayes the Lord made heauen, earth, and al that therein is, ſo in 6000. yeeres the Lord ſhall gouerne this world, being ſubiect to generation and corruption: and as the ſeauenth day he reſted, ſo in the 7000. ſhall he (hauing gatheredtogether his Church by the preaching 'of his word) bring all to euerlaſting reſt and peace. 2. As the Sabaoth was inſtituted in the eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the ſixt day. So by this Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, being vnderſtood the laſt Saba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oth, in the end of the laſt 2000. yeres or a little before, ſhall come the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Sabaoth, when all ſhall reſt. 3. As the ſix firſt Fathers, <hi>Adam, Seth, Enos, Cainan, Malaltel, Gared,</hi> are deade, and <hi>Enoch,</hi> the ſeauenth from <hi>Adam,</hi> was tranſlated into Heauen aliue, and ſawe no death: So for the ſpace of 6000. yeeres, the world, and death in the world ſhall bee and in the 7000. ſhall be bleſſedneſſe and immortalitie.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:150657:30"/>To ſhew the errour of this Propheſie, in falſe computation of yeares, it will more trouble your Honorable and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicious cares, then edify your hearts; onely thus much, know that there were before the Law aboue two thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand and fiue hundred yeres, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law ſewer then two thouſand. Beſids this, the opinion wants a grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke: for it hath no Scripture for Euidence, now where that founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion failes, there the building fals.</p>
            <p>But, what ſhall be vnder the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, wee ſhall not know vntill the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit day come: at what time, euery Mans bill of accounts ſhall be put in by appointment of the Creator of Time, and wages (God make vs mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while good ſeruants) giuen in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar to all. Some haue ſuppoſed, that becauſe Chriſt liued vpon the earth 32. yeeres and ſome ſix moneths: that therefore the Time vnder the Goſpel ſhall bee ſo long: for, ſay they, The Church hath a relation to Chriſt, and the body of the one, a type of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So then, as the naturall bodie
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:150657:30"/>tinued on earth 32. yeares, ſo ſhall the miſtical body; the Goſpell, the Church wee who are his members: prouided ſtill, that ſith at the end of theſe yeares, ſay they, ſhal be the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Iubiiee of our ſoules; that in the <hi>Interim,</hi> euery one of theſe yeeres haue a relation to the <hi>Moſaicall Iubile,</hi> that after ſo many fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es bee expired, the end ſhall come. But this being but o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, and the opinion of ſome, I leaue it in haſt to your reuerend opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions now, and to beeſcanned by the opinions of all at leaſure hereafter: only deſiring you to conſider with mee thus much, That all ages of man are limited to a certaine num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of yeeres, except the laſt part of old age.</p>
            <p>Infancie is reckoned to holde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the third or fourth yeare, Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode vntill ten yeeres, Pubertie vnto e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ighteene, youth vnto fiue and twentie, Courage vntill thirtie fiue, or fourtie yeres, Conſtant age vnto fiftie, lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>piſh age vntil 65 only decrepit croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedage hathno time of yers preſixt, but
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:150657:31"/>euen to laſt vntill the laſt, and the laſt gaſpe, bee it ſooner or farther off, to be the Stage, poſt or bound of tha. So likewiſe this laſt age of the world cannot bee determined, vntill by the Determiners appointment wee ſee a certaine determination. In the meane time, let vs redeeme the time, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the time; Let vs redeem the time or euilnes of the time, with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our liues. Let vs take his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell who gaue the beſt councell, euen councell for our ſoules. To watch and pray leaſt that day come vpon vs vna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wares and finde vs vnprouided. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider at that day what a Iudge we ſhal ſee, afrowning Iudge, he that damned the poore ſeruant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.28. for hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Talent, and bringing him onely his owne without inereſt. Hee that damned the poore ſoule, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.13. for comming to the marriage feaſt without his wedding garment. Hee that damned the fiue fooliſh virgins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.12. for not coming iumpe at the houre; and finall threatneth to dame all thoſe that worke iniquite.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:150657:31"/>
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41. Doe not wee reade how he caſt out <hi>Adam,</hi> the firſt man, for ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting an apple? Drowned the old world wholly, for wicked imaginations, al but <hi>Noah</hi> and his family, ſaued by a ſeely Arke of pine-trees? Reiected <hi>Saul</hi> and caſt him out of his Kingdome for ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig the Amalekites? Puniſhed <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man otherwiſe after his owne heart, with plagues, and his rebellious ſonne; for the committed acts of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ultery and murther? Threw the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels out of heauen. That light as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> thinkes, which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeakes of in the firſt of <hi>Geneſis?</hi> Turnd <hi>Lots</hi> wife into a piller of Salt? And then, <hi>Qui Angelis, &amp; pijs non pepercit, Hee who neither ſparde the Angels, nor good men, how ſhall wee wretched Sinners looke to eſcape?</hi> It is good for vs to thinke v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon theſe things, and to conſider that Our redemption draweth nigher now, then when we firſt beleeued. <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11. For if <hi>Paul</hi> held thoſe the laſt daies wherein he liued, who liued ſo many yeeres ſince, euen but 37. yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſts Paſſion; and beheaded in
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:150657:32"/>the 14. yoeere of <hi>Nero,</hi> what may we think of ours? The great Papiſt <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> affirmes that we haue not 400. to come: but be it, wee had 4000. to the worlds end, what is that to vs? The Pſalmiſt ſayth; <hi>Our daeyes are but three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore yeeres and ten: and if they bee of ſtrength, foureſcore yeers,</hi> and if ſo, all is but labour and ſorrow, cut off and we ſoone gone. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90 10. And <hi>Hier.</hi> ſaith, <hi>Sin amplius vixerimus,</hi> If wee liue aboue 80. yeeres it is no life to be called, but a death rather. Now when we die, the world is at an end with vs, we goe to the houſe of our age, and come forth no more to tell any tales. Wherfore, Ieſus make vs ready againſt death comes, and then Mercy will make vs happy when iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t coms. The very period of the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment time, ſome ſay, ſhall be at mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. <hi>Quia illahora Angelus Egyptum deuaſtauit, eademque hora electos ſuos de mundo liberabt,</hi> Becauſe in that houre, ſay they, the Angel did ſlay the Firſt-borne in Egypt; and that in that houre will hee deliuer his elect from
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:150657:32"/>Egypt of this world. Some ſay, <hi>Econ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> The iudgement time ſhall be in the day, either becauſe the Prophets doe call it, <hi>The day of the Lord;</hi> Or elſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that night if the time of night, ſhall be as bright as the day. Others ſay, whoſe opinion <hi>Iſodore</hi> citeth, that, The generall Reſurrection ſhall be in the ſame night, wherein our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour made his Reſurrection: that is, On Eaſer euen, a the feaſt of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer; and for that cauſe, ſaith hee, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny in the Primitiue Church of the faithfull, did watch that whole night, as expecting the Iudges comming, if we may beleene this Author. But theſe men I anſwere, firſt with that worthy father; <hi>Haec eſt fidei regnla dixit Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, dixit Apoſtulus, This is the rule of Faith,</hi> to ſay; <hi>Thus ſaid Chriſt, thus the Apoſtle.</hi> Now this is more then Chriſt or his Apoſtles ſaide, and ſo more then you or I muſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue.</p>
            <p>Next, for that they ſpeake of the Night time, I anſwere, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Aug. It ſhalbe, Nocte rerum,</hi> In
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:150657:33"/>the niht of the knowledge of actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s; <hi>Non temporum, Not in the night ſeaſn of time.</hi> Or els I ſay with he meaning of the Text, <hi>He ſhall come in the night,</hi> that is, Suddenly, vnexpected, when no man ſo much as dreameth on his then comming: and as in the night things are done that men know nor, ſo that time ſhall be when men thinke not. This is ſure, whenſoeuer it ſhall be <hi>A Trumpe ſhall blowe, Inerrorem, To terrifie:</hi> As <hi>Theophilact</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi> 24 <hi>ait; And a ſhrill cry ſhall bee ſo lowde, that All Soules in Heauen and Hell, and bodies in the graue ſhal heare, and at the hearing thereof appear before the Iudge.</hi> Who as <hi>Beda in cap.</hi> 21. <hi>Lucae,</hi> ſaith; <hi>Ea forma electis apparebit, qua in mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te apparuit, reprobis vero in ca forma qua in Cruce pependit, Sall appeere to his choſen in that forme wherein hee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to Peter, lames, and Iohn on the mountaine,</hi> that is, <hi>gloriouſl, his face and clothes gliſtering. Mat.</hi> 17.2. <hi>But to the reprobate hee ſhall appeare in that forme and ſhape which he had, when hee hanged on the Croſſe.</hi> Let vs then
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:150657:33"/>who deſire and hope for ſaluation, worke it by faith, and ſerue God here, that that bleſſed day may be welcome to vs hereafter, and how God will be ſerued. Old <hi>Hier.</hi> tels you, It will bee better by Aduerbs then by Verbs. <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat quiſque vt bonum opus, bene &amp; bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na intentione faciat; quia non bonum fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, ſed bene facere laudabile eſt, non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim in eo quod facimus, ſed quod bene facimus. Let euery one,</hi> ſaith he <hi>do good workes well, and with a good minde, for the praiſe is, not in the doing good, but in the doing well.</hi> Example be the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſie, he did good: I faſt twiſea week, I giue tythes of all I poſſeſſe. I am no Extortioner, vniuſt, adulterer. <hi>Lu.</hi> 18.2. But he did not well, for he wanted a good intention, which hee had not, and waned not a proud heart, which he had. Wherefore he ſaid, <hi>Not like this Publican. Ver.</hi> 2. And Chriſt ſaide, <hi>Not iuſtified. Verſ.</hi> 14. Thus all vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate perſons may doe <hi>Bonum, Good:</hi> but not <hi>Bne, Well:</hi> they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doe good well, becauſe they haue not in the ſight of God a good will:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:150657:34"/>the perſon before God is not plau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, becauſe bee wants Faith: nor the worke to GOD acceptable, ſith it wants not ſinne, <hi>What is not of Fath is ſinne,</hi> Romanes 14.23. 3. The end, <hi>to iudge the world,</hi> is the third part of my text, and this third part is taken in fiue ſneſes. Firſt, for all creatures in the world. Secondly, for all mankinde. Thirdly, for the elect. Fourthly, for the reprobates. Fifthly, for the deſires of the world, as luſts of the yes, deſire of the heart, pride of life: and in the ſecond ſeneſe, for all mankinde is <hi>worlde,</hi> in my text properly taken: for God ſhall iudge all mankinde, good and badde, and bring them all to iudgement. In the twentieth Chapter of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> and twelfth verſe, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the dead both great &amp; ſmall ſtand before God for their iudgeent: <hi>and the bookes were opened, and euory one was iudged acording to the things written in thoſe bookes: and the Sea gaue vp her dead and death &amp; hell gaue vp his dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A queſtion is heere mooued, how
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:150657:34"/>the damned ſoules in hell, and the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels the fallen Angels ſhall be iudged at the laſt day, that are iudged already at this day?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Solu.</hi> I anſwere, that in reſpect of condemnation they ſhal not at the laſt day be iudged; ſeeing they before hand are condemned by Gods eternall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, by his word, by their owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences: but in regard of aggrauation they ſhal be iudged, becauſe their pains ſhall be increaſed, &amp; themſelues ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lookt vnto, for hurting the godly any more. In this world <hi>Peter</hi> was ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, &amp; <hi>Iob</hi> was wounded: in the next world they are and ſhall be bleſſed: &amp; the bleſſed ſhal be crowned, crowned with a crowne of immortality, white array, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.5. And thus much by the way let me tell you, as I paſſe along this third part of my text: that White ſhall be the laſt apparell that we ſhall laſtly weare, it ſhall be the laſt weare which we ſhall weare, and it wil weare laſtingly: euen ſo long as this mortall ſhall weare immortality, after this mortall hath put on immortality.</p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:150657:35"/>
            <p>White is a colour betokening pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and ſo the fitter colour for Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where als is Puritie. It is the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour which wee ſhall haue in Heaen, where no impure, nor vncleane thing is. <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.5. This white was the colour wherewith Chriſt was moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and this where ſhall bee the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour wherewith wee ſhall be crowned. White was a color wherewith Chriſt was clad when hee was in miſerie <hi>Luk.</hi> 23.15. And white ſhall bee that co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, wherewith wee ſhall be clothed when we are in maieſtie.</p>
            <p>In the 1. of <hi>Iohn, chap.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 2. It is ſaid, <hi>Wee ſhall bee like vnto him:</hi> that is, as <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith, <hi>Corpus noſrum, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mile reddet conforme corpori ſuo glorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, Hee ſhall make our clay bodies like his gloriou body.</hi> And in the 17. of <hi>Mat ver.</hi> 2. the Text ſaith, <hi>When he ea transfigured his face didſhine like the Sonne, and his clothes were as white as the light.</hi> So hee is white, and wee ſhall be white.</p>
            <p>Now to this great Iudgement, (to which wee muſt come, when our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:150657:35"/>ſhall haue on this incorup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible white) there are three <hi>Apparators</hi> that doe ſummon the World, as my text hath it: Vs, I ſay, Mankind who liue in the world. 1. <hi>Infirmitas paena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis, Infirmitie penall.</hi> 2 <hi>Senectus tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralis, Age temporarie.</hi> 3 <hi>Mors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euitabilis, Death ineuitable.</hi> And theſe three ſammon all to Iudgement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all are ſublunary, and ſubiect to corruption: all had a beginning, ad muſt haue an ending, euen ended by him, by whom they were begunne: him I ſay, <hi>That hath appointed a day in which hee will Iudge the World.</hi> The firſt of theſe <hi>Apparators</hi> doth threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, the ſecond doth proſecute, the third doth produce. Infirmitie threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth miſery, Age doth proſecute ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamitie: and Death doth bring vs with him into the High Commiſſion Court of <hi>Iudicium ſpeciale, Our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler Iudgement,</hi> before the Iudge of the World, to anſwere for iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, where if our Lawyers bee not good, the Cauſe will goe againſt vs.</p>
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:150657:36"/>
            <p>We ſee in theſe daies that booke-ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes alter, and what is Law before one Iudge, is ouerruled by another: but ſure I am that what is Law in this world, ſhall not bee Law in the world to come. Elſe would I deeme no peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſooner ſaued then Lawyers, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they who are good and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable Lawyers, (as we haue diuers) ſuch as will talke for their Clyents now; I ſuppoſe they would plead har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for themſelues then. 1. Infirmitie doth ſummon vs, for that is a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the firſt ſinne, (which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was Luſt, as many of the old writers held it out of <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.2. or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was ignorance as ſme ſay: or whether Pride, to haue an equalizing of themſelues with God, as <hi>Hierome, Gregory Nazianzene</hi> prooue, and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine Tract in Iob.</hi> 49. affirmeth) that I leaue becauſe my text doth not find it. And this infirmity is, partly in the ſoule, which delighteth not in heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things as it ſhould; but in earthly things as it ſhould not: partly in the body, ſubiect to hunger, cld, naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:150657:36"/>and as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith: <hi>Man borne of a woman hath but a ſhort time to liue, and is full of miſeries. Iob.</hi> 14.1. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fides miſeries naturall, of which as <hi>Gallen</hi> ſaith, there are three hundred; as yes ſbiect to blindneſſe, bleered<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thickneſſe: Eares to deafeneſſe, impoſtumes, fouleneſſe: Mouth and tongue to cankers, toothache, dumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: Head to rewmes, megrims gid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dines: Throat to ſtuffings, ſtranglings hoarcenes: hands and legs to palſies, gowtes, feeblenes: there are alſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries accidentall, impriſonings, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nummings perils by fire, waters, cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, men. Theſe all are miſeries, and all theſe miſeries are all meſſengers; euen Remembrancers to put vs in mind of the iudgement day at hand: for mans miſeries are like <hi>Iobs</hi> bad tidings, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.23. the end of ne euill meſſage was the beginning of another. 2. Age doth cite vs that when we ſee our hairs gray, our bodies bend, our eies dimme all decline; wee cannot chooſe but thinke of our ende at hand vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, <hi>Nolumus agnoſcere quod igno.
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:150657:37"/>norare uon poſſumus, Wee will not know what wee cannot but know.</hi> The very paſſing by graues, the vewing of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents, (fading memories, for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numents and all muſt dye) the ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Nature, the impayring of ſtrength: theſe things, me thinks, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing cnſidered, ſhould teach vs to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that, which will cloſe vp our eyes, ſtoppe vp our breath, lay vs in a companileſſe bed, a darke narrowe ſix foote grae. 3 Death (this <hi>Vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timum terribilium, Laſt of all terrible things,</hi> as <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> cals it) doth ſerue a certaine vncertaine Summon vpon vs for Iudgement, ſith after the one, inſtantly comes the other, and there is no purging third place, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts vainely, vilely ſalſely hold. <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues</hi> dyed and was in Hell in torments, <hi>Lazarus</hi> dyed, an was carried into <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brahams</hi> boſome. <hi>Duo ſunt habitacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, in igne aeterno, in regno aeterno, &amp; non eſt quis medins Locus vt poſsit nemo eſſe niſi cum Diabalo, qui non eſt cum Chriſto, Thers but two pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtine in the euerlaſting</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:150657:37"/>kingdome &amp; in eternall fire, and there is no third place, that he who is not with God, muſt needes be with the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell.</p>
            <p>Many things there are that put vs in minde of death, &amp; death puts in minde of iudgement: and when <hi>Mors fecit quod potuit,</hi> death hath done what muſt be; <hi>Indicium faciet quod erit:</hi> Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will performe what ſhall be. One faith, God will one day aske vs all at the laſt day three queſtions. 1. <hi>Qui.</hi> 2. <hi>Qnales.</hi> 3. <hi>Quanti.</hi> What we are by creation, what by continuation, how we haue profited. Suppoſe the Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty examine any of vs here vpon theſe interrogatories, we cannot but anſwer <hi>Ad idem</hi> directly to the queſion, for it is follie to lie to him, who knowes better then we. 1. Well then for our creation, we will confeſſe that wee are <hi>Ad imaginem dei facti;</hi> Veſſels (take heeue we make not our ſelues vaſſels) made after his owne image. 2. If we be asked, what we are by continuation: why that the Diuell without (who fees our actions, harts, our counſels knows
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:150657:38"/>our very thoughts. <hi>Quatenus animus externis ſe prodit ſigus.</hi> As our minde bewraies it ſelfe by outward ſignes, as <hi>P. Mat.</hi> in 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> ſaith: who ſhall <hi>Aſtare iudicio,</hi> be by the Lord at iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as one ſaith, and whom <hi>Augu.</hi> brings in pleading his inditement a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs, thus, Theſe ſinners, O iuſt iudge are thine, <hi>Per gratiam,</hi> through grace in which they were made, but mine <hi>Per culpam</hi> through ſinne, by which they are marde: thine as they were framed, mine as they are fowled: thine in mercie, mine in iuſtice; thine by thy death, mine by their life, &amp;c. can tell: and our conſcience within, (which is as a thouſand witneſſes) can teſtifie. 3. But when he comes to <hi>Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum profecimus,</hi> How much wee haue profited, though with that idle ſeruant <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.22. <hi>Ex ore noſtro,</hi> Out of our owne mouth he might iudge vs, ye out of his mercie fraught with iuſtice, he goes to his owne bookes, ſearcheth the records, there hee waies our ſinnes and Chriſts merits together in a ballance, to ſee how our faith
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:150657:38"/>can cacth holde to turne the ſcales. I pray God therefore we may liue in this world like iuſt men: for they liue like <hi>Paul,</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> liued by the <hi>Faith of the Sonne of God. Gal.</hi> 2.20. So if wee liue like iuſt men, wee ſhall haue the rewards of iuſt men; euen the kingdome of heauen, where God and his Sonne is, and whethe God and his Sonne Ieſus ſend vs all. A queſtion more curious then need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full is moued by ſome about this day of iudgement: to wit, whether the definitiue ſentence ſhall goe and paſle on vs Mentally, or Vocaly; that is, whether it ſhall bee onely in mens mindes, hearts, and conſciences: or whether wee ſhall all be called name by name? It ſhould ſeeme <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> thought it to bee <hi>Vocall,</hi> for <hi>De ciuit. liber</hi> 20. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Circa me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium capitis,</hi> He hath theſe words. <hi>Per quot dies tendatur iudicium hoc, incertum eſt, ſed Scripturarum more ſanctarum diem poni ſolere pro tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pre, nemo qui illas litter as quam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet negligenter, ligerit, neſcit:</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:150657:39"/>How many daies that iudgement time ſhall holde, it is vncertaine; but its the cuſtme of the Scripture to put a day for the length of time, and none haue beene ſo little conuerſant in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but know this: Had <hi>Auguſtine</hi> thought it ſhuld be mentall, he neede not haue ſpoken of Daies, for it would haue a ſhort cut, &amp; be ſoone diſpatcht. On the other ſide, Some ſuppoſeit ſhall be <hi>Mental</hi> onely, and they bring the not Canonicall Scripture for proofe, <hi>Wiſedeme cap.</hi> 4. <hi>ver.</hi> 19. <hi>Without a voice he ſhall burſt them</hi> Others hold, that the <hi>Sentence of iudgement ſhall bee</hi> both <hi>Mentall</hi> and <hi>Vocal;</hi> becauſe the Iudge ſhall iudge both as God and man: therefore that his iudgement ſhall be both after a diuine and an humaine manner. But for theſe opinion, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I rater thinke with the laſt: yet I ſay, Of ſecret things which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the creator, there can bee no ſure determination by the creature. Thus I pray, O Lord increaſe our faith tell our death, ſo ſhall we be ſure to be Chriſts when wee are dead, and then
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:150657:39"/>ſhall we not care whether the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment be vocall, or mentall, ne or both. Some are of opinion, that ſo many men ſhall be ſaued; as diuelsfell: Some that ſo many ſhall be ſaued, as Angels ſtood. A third ſort ſay, That there ſhall be in heauen two wals, the one of Angels, the other of men, and that the ruine of the Angels ſhall be reſtored with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, the other wals ſhall haue ſo many Saints to make vp that, as there are both Angels and Virgins. But theſe vncertaine opinions of men, I leaue to the future trial of ſuch holy men, as ſhall inioy bleſſedneſſe there, where they ſhall truely iudge of theſe opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: In the meane time my <hi>Quaere is,</hi> whether the number of the Angels that ſtood, or the diuels that fell, be the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Of the Angels that ſtood, ſome thinke they are moe in number, now remaining, then all the material things created: and the Prophet ſpeaking of them, ſets down no determinate num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of them, but they are thouſand thouſands, and ten thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands. <hi>Deut.</hi> 7.10. that is, they are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150657:40"/>
               <hi>Quoad nos,</hi> in reſpect of vs. As for the diuels that fell, thogh with <hi>Bucanus</hi> in his booke of Angels, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that there is <hi>Paene innnmerabilis numerus,</hi> Almoſt a number without number, not to be numbred: yet I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that more ſtood by the mercy of God, then were ſuffired to fall in his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: onely what I thinke in this to be true, I know not; This I know, if that the redeemer of our ſoules hath written all our here-names in the Cataloque of the holy ones that ſhall be ſaued, it wil not hurt vs, though wee know not the number of them that ſhal be ſued: true faith will aſſure vs of the one now, and bring vs aſſuredly where we ſhall know the other hereafter, 4 The fourth part of my text, is the manner how we ſhall be iudged: ſet downe to be <hi>In righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> for the goodneſſe of the vpright Iudge, may be a warrant to vs for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe in iudgement. Righteouſnes in God is <hi>De eſſentia,</hi> A part of his eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, nay it is God: for <hi>Quicquid eſt in deo deus eſt,</hi> Whatſocuer is in God is God: therefore to haue him giue
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:150657:40"/>
               <hi>Rectum in dicium,</hi> right iudgement, it is no doubt <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaith, <hi>He is inſt in all his waies, and righteous in all his workes:</hi> and according to a worke of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe he will iudge the world: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſaith, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 35. <hi>Iudge, me according to ty righteouſneſſe,</hi> True iuſtice is <hi>Suum cuique tribuere.</hi> To giue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one his owne, ſaith the Philoſopher: and ſo will God, render to cuery one according to their workes, be they good or euill. Among many pettie Iudges, <hi>Ignorantia legis,</hi> the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the law maketh a default in iudgement. But our Iudge was the lawgiuer himſelf, &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there needeth no writ of errour be ſued out among all Iudges <hi>Ignoratia facti,</hi> the ignorance of the fact for want of true Euidence may produce a wrong ſentence: but this Iudge is <hi>Serntator cordium,</hi> The ſearcher of all hearts, he knoweth al thoughts, as the Pſalmiſt ſaith: Yea, knoweth what wee will doe before it is done, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt needes iudge aright when it is done. This Iudge who ſhall iudge vs, was once iudgd himſelfe: and we
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:150657:41"/>who one day muſt be iudged, doe at this day oft in dge others, but yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and our ſelues ſhall be once iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by him, who will one day be iudge of all: yea, and that in righteouſneſle, as himſelfe was not iudged. <hi>Pilate</hi> the iudge yeelded that he found no fault in him at all, and yet againſt all right, with more wrong he gaue ſentence vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him: the tenour whereof the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts haue concealed, yet in an old writer, I finde it thus recorded, <hi>Ieſus Nazari, ſeductor populi, quem gens tua namprobauit regem, propter contentum Caeſareae magiſtatis, praecipio te primum, flagellari ſecundum principum ſtatuta, deinde in cruce ileuari: I lictor, expedi cruſom: Ieſus of Nazareth, a ſeducer of the people, one whom thine owne nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on haue allowed King: for contempt of the Maieſtie of Ceſar: I doe command that according to the Lawes of Princes, Thou be firſt whipt &amp; then lifted vp to the Croſſe: Goe Sergeant prepare the Gibbet.</hi> Thus dealt <hi>Pilate</hi> with him, in whoſe mouth was found no guile: then what ſhall become of vs, in whom is found
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:150657:41"/>ſo much? <hi>For if the iuſt man fall ſeauen times a day. Pro.</hi> 24.16. How ſhall they eſcape whoſe life is continual fal? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, my text ſaith, we ſhall be iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in righteouſneſſe, we ſhall haue our due, and beare but our owne burthen; &amp; yet that without helpe, God knowes is too heauie. Were the Iudges in the world; like the Iudge of the world, to iudge all in righteouſneſſe, oh it were well: <hi>Socrates</hi> laught becauſe hee ſaw great theeues hang vp little the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ues but we may grieue to ſee poore flies intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled, where Bees paſle through with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any ſtoppage; the beſt is this, All are but Stewards, and al muſt be count<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. <hi>Habent ſupremi iudices ſuperiorem iudicem.</hi> Chiefe Iudges ſhall haue the chiefe Iudge to iudge the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, if they for fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor do not giue true iudgement: If in a country thou ſeeſt the oppreſſion of the poore, &amp; the defrauding of iudgement &amp; iuſtice, be not aſtonied at the matter, for he that is higher then the higheſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardeth, and there be higher then they. <hi>Eccl.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Si tanta in terris haberetur fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, quanta in caelis exſpectatur merces,</hi> If
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:150657:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:150657:42"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:150657:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:150657:43"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:150657:44"/>men had ſo much faith on earth, as they expect teward with the ſonne of man in heauen, good Lord what a world ſhould we haue? But farth of late hath betaken it ſelfe to it wings, and is fled from peoples hearts; godlines is become as a vagrant, gees vp and downe, from towne to towne, from partie to partie for want of imployment: the intertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereof is a paſſeport, whipt away from the earth, and ſent home to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, the place where it was borne. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion is fixt in the ſphere of no mans heart, there is none that doth good, no not one, it is now Plannet-like ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times nigher, ſometimes farther off. &amp; he who giues it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be-rome. This mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth diſcards it, the moneth following: we haue ſo many temporizers, that few ſhall be eternized: ſo many on earth, that few in heauen. So much diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that <hi>Momus</hi> his wiſh to <hi>Iupiter</hi> (as the Poets faint) to haue a glaſlewindow in mens breſts, to diſeerne betweene their hearts, and their words, would be a Boone to the world. So little fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delitie, that an honeſt plaine dealing
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:150657:44"/>man, is <hi>Animal rarum,</hi> like a nightra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, ſeldome ſeene: ſo that we may inſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with <hi>Diogines</hi> take a candle and a lanthorne at noone day, and ſay <hi>Quae, ro hommem</hi> I ſeeke a man. We liue in an age, I cannot ſay the leaſt (God be thanked, it is the laſt) but I may too truely ſay the worſt: and as the Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicke ſaid of an Italian, Take a light and ſeeke cuerie hole, and not finde a worſe; ſo ſay I of our times. Take paines and ſearch all ſtories, and not finde the like. Hence I inferre that theſe bee the laſt daies and fartheſt times of our Sauiours comming: that the appointed day is at our very heeles, becauſe now our good friends doubt may be eaſily reſolued, when the Son of man ſhall come, ſhall he finde faith on the earth. <hi>Luk.</hi> 18.8. Yea. doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome, and but a little, and yet ſome, elſe the world could not ſtand. For I dare ſay, we have ſome ſaithfull <hi>Eliahs</hi> that obtaine raine in time of neede: ſome holy <hi>Moſes,</hi> that ſtand in the gap of Gods wrath, to keep his iudg me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs: ſome bleſſed <hi>Abrahams</hi> that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:150657:45"/>pleade with God, euen the caſe of this citie, elſe I beleeue that the wals here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of had beene downe long ere this. Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention is the hart of pollicie, and let vs learne Chriſtian policie to preuent, the policie ſhall bee that which <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth vs, <hi>To amend our lines. Act.</hi> 2.38. Euery one to mend one: the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uention will-be this, we ſhall b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> neſther puniſhed with the wicked, nor ſhall we periſh with the wicked. Not pnniſhed; <hi>My people be not partakers of her ſinnes, leaſt you beare a part of her plagues. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poc.</hi> 18.4. <hi>Not periſh He that turnes to the Lord, his ſouleiſhall liue. Ezech</hi> 18. Let vs then who deſire to eſcape both pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing and periſhing too, looke to all Chriſt tels vs, ignorance ſhall excuſe no man: the ſeruant gaue his maiſter none anſwere at his reture the text <hi>ait,</hi> and the reaſon is giuen by <hi>Chri, Vt ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus in die inditij ceſſare excuſatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem peccati.</hi> To giue vs to vnderſtand that at the day of iudgement none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe will ſarue the turne: only my text tels vs, we ſhall be iudged in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and right is no wrong. In righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:150657:45"/>God created man, in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes created man ſhould liue, in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe liuing man ſhould die, and in righteouſneſſe liuing and dead menſhal be iudged, Gifts blinde the eies of the wiſe, but our Iudge will not be bribed: Iudges may be partiall to parties but God is no accepter of perſons: Iudges may be moued with pittie, but our now Ieſus will be then <hi>Iudex.</hi> A iudge, all for iuſtice; <hi>In iſto tantum ſeculo miſericors eſt. Hier. in</hi> 105 <hi>Pſalme,</hi> Onely in this world God is mercifull, in the next world mercy hath no ſeare, pittie hath no plea. Let all then take heede how they liue in this interſtiticall time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore iudgement, leaſt being found gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, when they ſhall be conuented be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the great Iudge at the great Aſſiſe of the world: they haue that diſmail Mittimns made, of <hi>Ite,</hi> to their diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſoules from the hands of him who will iudge in righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The ſift part of my text, is the partie, who muſt iudge vs Your honor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, worſhipfull and religious patience hath afforded me eies and eares in this
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:150657:46"/>more then two houtes trauell through the way of my tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: I beſeech you let not now my prolixitie make you thinke ouerlong the time, to ſtay vntil the end of my tourney: that you may heare the whole diſcourſe; for thaſt a pace, and preſſe towards the marke. It any then aske me, who this iudge ſhall be? who the man is, that is appointed to iudge the world? I anſwere, It is the man Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt God and man, who died for man to iudge man. For he that was God was borne vpon the earth as man for vs, he that was borne vpon the earth as man for vs, wrought vpon the earth as God for vs; he who wrought vpon the earth as God for vs, died vpon the ereſle as man for vs, and he who died vpon the croſle as man for vs, roſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine the third day as God for vs to make vs the adopted ſons of his father? Now he that was thus borne, did thus worke, ſo die, and ſo riſe againe: he who was God and man, to adopt man, ſhall iudge man.</p>
            <p>The truth of this appeares out of our creede: <hi>Where we beleeue in Ieſus
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:150657:46"/>Chriſt, who aſcended into heauen &amp; ſhall thence come to iudge both the quicke and the dead,</hi> tappeares out of <hi>Rom</hi> 14.10 where the text ſaith, We ſhal al appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt, &amp; it is plaine, <hi>loh.</hi> 5.22. <hi>The father indgeth no man, but hath giuen all iudgement to the ſonne,</hi> which words are ſpoken by our Sau our himſelfe, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the Iudge.</hi> The Sonne then ſhall be iudge, &amp; yet we muſt not think that the Father and the holy Ghoſt are ſeduced fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this iudgement: but this we muſt hold, that the ſonne Ieſus Chriſt our Sauiour ſhal iudge immediatly, really, locally, perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, viſibly, the other two ſhall iudge inuiſibly, onely by giuing their conſent. Chriſt ſhall execute ſentence vpon the world perſonally, <hi>In forma hominis,</hi> In the forme of a man, in the ſame forme which he tooke on him when he was on earth. Whereupon <hi>Bernard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Vulnera ſeruanit in diem iudicij: vt videant ea Iudaes, &amp; confund<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tur He hath kept his wounds vnto the day of iudgement, that the Iewes may ſee them, and bee confounded.</hi> The whole Trinitie
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:150657:47"/>ſhall iudge Authoritatiue, with equall authoritie; but Chriſt ſhall iudge exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutatiue, with execution of ſentence: be cauſe <hi>Iudex debet eſſe manifeſtus omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus iudicandis.</hi> The Iudge muſt ſhew himſelfe, and be manifeſt to al that ſhall be iudged. For wee muſt know that the Father and the holy Ghoſt ſhal not be ſeene, according to their diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all that muſt be at iudgement, for then all ſhould be bleſſed, and all ſhould be bleſſed, for the ſeeing of God is bleſſedneſſe, and bleſſedneſſe is the ſeeing of God. For as in hell, <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma paena,</hi> The greateſt puniſhment is the priuation of the ſeeing God: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Chryſ.</hi> ſaith. <hi>Impij non tantum do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebunt de ipſo ſupplicio, quam quod repel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntur a tale conſortio. The wicked ſhall not ſo much lament the paines which they ſuffer: as the company from which they are kept.</hi> So in heauen the greateſt happineſſe (all being happineſſe, and being all happineſſe) is to ſee God, that is, as wee can ſee him, and as he will bee ſeene. For in the world to come God ſhall bee ſeene of all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:150657:47"/>whole, but not of all wholly: of all whole becauſe the whole number of the Elect ſhall ſee him, but nor of all wholly, becauſe God is infinite. God ſhal be ſeen in the world to come ſo far forth as is fit, either for the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator to reueal himſelfe to his creature, or for the creature to ſee the creator: but the whole Deity neyther is, nor can bee ſeene: for bee is a ſpirite, and <hi>Deum nemo vidit unquam,</hi> neuer man ſaw God at any time. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.12 Therefore whereas <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>I ſhall ſee God in my fleſh cap.</hi> 19.26. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wee ſhall ſee him as hee is.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>verſ:</hi> 2. &amp; whereas it is of <hi>Iacob Gen.</hi> 32. and of <hi>Moſes, Exod</hi> 33. ſaid, that <hi>they ſaw God.</hi> And whereas <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Wee ſhall ſee him face to face,</hi> 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 13.12. Wee muſt not take the words litterally, but the meaning of the words: <hi>That we ſhall ſee God as hee will be ſeene.</hi> Wherefore by this ſeeing of God in the world to come, is meant the cleere knowledge which wee ſhall the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue of God, which knowledge ſhal not be with the eies of our body, but the eyes of our mind: and that too, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:150657:48"/>by meanes, as by his word, works or outward ſignes: or elſe without means by ſpeciall Reuelation: For one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God hath ſeene God, <hi>Iohn</hi> 6.46. For I do bele ue that in the world to come, there ſhall be diuerſity of ioyes, one ſtarre differeth from another in glery, 1. Cor. 15.41. that is as <hi>Wirth</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the learned expound it there ſhall be <hi>Honoris &amp; gloriae graedus vna tamen &amp; eadem: faelicitas aeterna,</hi> De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of honour and glory, and yet but one eternall felicity. Alſo my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour ſaith, <hi>In my fathers houſe there be many dwelling places, Iob.</hi> 14.2. Which although <hi>Caluin</hi> obſeruing the worde <hi>many</hi> ſaith, the text doth not nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Diuers,</hi> as Difference in glory, and therefore thinketh that there ſhal be in heauen no degrees of glory; yet for mine owne particular, I belceue with them that thus expound this place. <hi>Multitudo manſionum differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam quoque gloriae ſignificat:</hi> the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of manfions, ſignifieth diuerſities of glory. But as in the oddes of ioyes I hold that the leaſt ſhall be full, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:150657:48"/>able to hold any more, nor deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring any more: ſo doubtleſſe the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of ſeeing God, ſhall be <hi>ex par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te videntis non viſi;</hi> Of the party ſeeing, not of him who is ſeene. Fill two veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of vnequall bigneſſe with any li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quor, and the bigger holds more then the leſſe, yet both are full: ſo an olde declined, or an ill imperfect eye ſeeth the Sunne much worſe then a young and perfect eye, and yet the Sunne ſhewes it ſelfe, and ſhieth to all alike. Thus doe I beleeue it will be between God and his Saints, the holy ones in the world to come. God is knowne 3. maner of waies. 1. <hi>Quod eſt.</hi> 2. <hi>Quid eſt</hi> 3. <hi>Sicut eſt.</hi> That heis, What he is, As he is. 1. That he is, &amp; ſo he is known to the Diuels and the wicked; <hi>Credunt demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes et trement:</hi> the Diuels beleeue there is a God, &amp; tremble, <hi>I am.</hi> 2.19. 2. What he is, and ſo is known to the Angels in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in our bleſſed cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try. 3. As he is, &amp; ſo he ſhalbe neither ſeen nor known neither of Saints nor wicked, neither in this world nor the world to come: for <hi>Finitum nequit comprehendere infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitum,</hi> They that are finit can neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:150657:49"/>what is infinite. The Church alſo at the laſt day ſhall iudge as Chriſt tels vs, <hi>Ye ſhall ſit on ſeats and iudge the twelue tribes of ſcaell, Luk</hi> 22.30. that is, as ſome expound it, <hi>Ibierunt omnes ſancti iudicis ſententiam approbantes.</hi> There ſhall be all the holy ones to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue Chriſts ſentence, and ſubſcribe to his iudgement.</p>
            <p>Vpon this text a woorthy writer ſaith thus, The Apoſtles iudge the world at this day, by the preaching of the Goſpell, whoſo beleeueth ſhall bee ſaued: at the laſt day the whole world ſhall be iudged by Chriſt, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Goſpell preached by the Apoſtles; and in this ſence, the Saints being members of Chriſt, <hi>Iudicabunt cum Chriſto mundum, et Angelos, hoc eſt, Diabolos,</hi> Shall iudge together with Chriſt the world &amp; the cuill An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels the Deuils: as wee may reade 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2. <hi>Muſculus</hi> expounds it thus. <hi>The faith of the Apoſtles ſhall take away aell excuſes from the Ifraelites, that is, At that day of iudgement ſhall riſe vp to condemne them, as our Sauiour tells the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:150657:49"/>people, Luke</hi> 11.31. <hi>The Queene of the South ſhall riſe in iudgement with the men of this generation, and condemne them, for ſhee came from the vtmoſt parts of the earth to heare the wiſedome of Salomon, and behold a greater then Salomon is heere: the men of Niniueh ſhall riſe in iudgement with this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration and ſhall condemne it, for they repented at the preaching of Ionas, and behold a greater then Ionas is heere.</hi> And as our Sauiour ſpeakes, <hi>Iohn</hi> 12.4. <hi>The worde that I haue ſpoken ſhall iudge you at the laſt day:</hi> otherwiſe we muſt know that Chriſt the Iudge ſhall ſit alone in iudgement. In that will be the bleſſed day, the day in which wee ſhall be bleſſed; and after which wee ſhall enioy eternall bleſſedneſſe in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. In heauen, <hi>Sciemus, amabimus, gaudebimus, laudabimus:</hi> We ſhall know, wee ſhall loue, wee ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, wee ſhall praiſe, ſaith <hi>Hugo.</hi> Firſt wee ſhall know God, his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells, his ſecrets, his iudgements, the cauſes, natures, beginning and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of all creatures ſaith this <hi>Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalis:</hi>
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:150657:50"/>yea I aſſure my ſelfe, that in Heauen we ſhall know one another: but how? Not with an earthly know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge: I ſuppoſe that ſhall vaniſh a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with all earthly deſire: ſith our will ſhall then bee the ſame with Gods will, wee ſhall bee glad to ſee them damned, whom God hath dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned; and them ſaued whom God hath made heyres of ſaluation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Branmelerus</hi> is of an opinion, that heauen wee ſhall know thoſe with whome on earth we haue conuerſed, as Parents. Kindred, friends, yea all the Patriarchs and Apoſtles, <hi>Adam, Abrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Moſes, Dauid, Peter, Paul,</hi> &amp; the reſt, euen thoſe that we neuer ſaw: his reaſons are. 1. Becauſe the Apoſtles in Mount Tabor at the time of Chriſts transfiguration, knew <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> whom they neuer ſaw before, <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.4. If they did ſo, being <hi>in corpore infirmo,</hi> In a body of infirmitie, what ſhall they and wee doe when we are <hi>In corpore glorioſo.</hi> In a body of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? 2. Againe, wee ſhall be, in heauen as Angels, and equall to them. <hi>Luke</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:150657:50"/>20.36. and the Angels in heauen doe aſſuredly know one another, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares, Dan 10.13. where the Angell that appeared to <hi>Daniel</hi> told him how he was withſtood by the Prince of <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiae;</hi> if hee had not knowne him, how could he haue diſtinguiſhed him to be that Prince? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3+ letters">
                  <desc>•••…</desc>
               </gap>eſide, if we ſhall know God himſelfe, as I haue ſhow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much more ſhall wee know one another: thus <hi>Adam</hi> beeing caſt into a ſleepe, knew his Wife <hi>Euah,</hi> and could ſay, <hi>This is fleſh of my fleſh, and bone of my bone;</hi> When as yet hee neuer before had ſeene her. But this hee did <hi>Spiritu ſancti ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, et vera Dei cognitione praeditus,</hi> Beeing full of the holy Spirite, and indued with the true knowledge of God, ſaith this Author: And <hi>Greg. Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al lib.</hi> 4. ſaith, <hi>Quia illic omnes commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni claritate conſpiciunt, non eſt quod ibi neſciant vbi Scientem omnia ſciunt;</hi> Becauſe that in Heauen with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon cleare brightneſſe, and bright cleareneſſe, all there doe ſee, it cannot be that they may bee <hi>neſcient,</hi> where
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:150657:51"/>they know him that knowes all, 2. <hi>Amabimus</hi> wee ſhall loue God, good things, one another; God, that there hath crowned vs; good things, that there are with vs: one another that there are all brethren among vs: for <hi>manent haec tria,</hi> now remaine theſe 3, Faith, Hope and Loue: But the chiefe of theſe is Loue, 1. Cor. 13.13, becauſe Faith and Hope are but in this world to crowne vs in the next, and when they haue obtained their ende, they leaue. But Loue doth neuer leaue vs, it goeth with vs to Heauen, where whileſt we liue, wee ſhall loue: there euer liue, and there euer loue. 3. <hi>Gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debimus,</hi> wee ſhall haue ioy without meaſure, without compare, without end: without meaſure, for it cannot bee equald: without compare, for it ſhall be infinite: without ende, for it ſhall be euerlaſting. 4. <hi>Laudebimus,</hi> wee ſhall praiſe God without griefe, without trouble, without wearineſſe, without griefe, for all reares ſhall bee wiped from our eyes; without trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nothing ſhall moleſt vs: without
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:150657:51"/>wearines, for no mortall accident ſhal comencere our bodies; ſith <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſaith, <hi>They ſhall bee ſeuen times cleer er then the glorious Sunne.</hi> O the glory of that happineſſe, thrice happy are they that are ſo happy; that kingdome where youth ſhal flouriſh without age, where life knowes none end, where beauty neuer fadeth, loue neuer coo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, ſickneſſe neuer pierceth, ioy ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ceaſeth. That kingdome where ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row is neuer felt, complaint neuer heard, mourning neuer ſeene, ill ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer feared. That kingdome where our knowledge ſhall bee perfected, our vnderſtanding ſhall be poliſhed, our acquaintance increaſed. That king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where our ſoules ſhall bee in felicity, our bodies in eternity, both ſoules and bodies in maieſty. Oh thriſe happy day, when ſoule and body ſhall there meere, and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come be that appointed day which brings with it this bleſſed day. The meditation of this day, &amp; theſe things, will teach vs many things; and as <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> gourd did comfort him, chap. 4.7.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:150657:52"/>ſo this may inſtruct vs. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.37. that kept him from heat, and this may ſhelter vs from danger. It may teach vs to watch and pray, ſith wee know not the time of our diſſolution; whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our ſpecial iudgement ſhall be in the morning of our youth, the noone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tide of our ſtrength, or the euening of our age: Whether we ſhall be <hi>Praemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti,</hi> forewarned, that we may be <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniti</hi> forearmd: or whether we ſhall haue a <hi>Scarbrough</hi> warning, ſuddenly be gone. We read of a certaine watery ſerpent, called <hi>Ephemeron,</hi> that <hi>Simul oritur &amp; moritur,</hi> no ſooner bred but dead. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> writes of certaine flies by the riuer <hi>Hippanis,</hi> that they are bredde in the morning, ſtrong at noone, and dead ere night. Theſe are the Emblemes of man, as in a map deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribing our mortality. Let vs then be warned, for <hi>Qui non cauet pauet;</hi> He feareth that takes no heed: <hi>Nemo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenda timet quimetuenda cauet,</hi> whoſo feareth what is to be preuented, nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth not preuent what is to be feared. <hi>Gregory</hi> ſaith, <hi>Nemo in huius vitae iti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:150657:52"/>torpeat, ne in Patria locum perdat; quiae enim adhuc bene licet agere ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, an cras liceat ignoramus:</hi> Let none goe dully in the iourney of this life, leaſt he looſe his place in the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly country: for though we know wee haue time to do well to day, we know not whether we ſhall liue to morrow, yea or nay. Let vs therfore confes our ſins, not to man as the Papiſts bid vs, who are <hi>Curioſum genus hominum ad cognoſcendam vitanialienam, deſidioſum ad corrigendam ſuam.</hi> A certain curious company of Shauelings to correct o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens liues, and ſtothfull in men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their owne: but to God, <hi>Is enim nunc vidit quae fiunt, &amp; poſtea punit eos qui paenitentiam non agunt:</hi> For hee ſeeth what we doe now, and puniſhes them that repent not, heereafter: If wee acknowledge our ſinnes, hee is faithful and iuſt to forgiue vs our ſins, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 1 9.2. It may teach vs to ſet a guard about our actions, &amp; a watch about our lips with good <hi>Dauid,</hi> leaſt we offend with our tongue. 3. It may teach vs to ſeaſon all our actions
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:150657:53"/>with diſcretion, leaſt at any time wee deale raſhly as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> did, when he did cut off <hi>Malcus</hi> eare. 4. It may teach vs obedience, with <hi>Noah</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide the Arke while the weather is calm: with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> it may make vs pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident, in time of plenty to lay vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a day of ſcarcity; in the Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer of our youth againſt the winter of our age.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Lot</hi> had aboade in <hi>Sodome</hi> in the time of burning, how could hee haue ſcaped? If we loue the world in this time of ſinning, how ſhal we be ſaued? We ſee in the example of <hi>Sodome,</hi> that what is offended at midnight, is puniſhed at noone day, for the ſunne did riſe vpon <hi>Sodome</hi> that day, and yet ſoone after came <hi>Sodomes</hi> deſtruction: now <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demes</hi> iudgement hath a reference to the laſt iudgement, thus. The light, or Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe is Gods iudgement, the night or <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes</hi> fall is the committing of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: the parallel is this whatſoeuer it committed in the night of the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of this world, ſhall be made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt in the Sun-riſe of the world to
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:150657:53"/>come. Laſtly, it may comfort vs who are Gods choſen, whoſe names are written in the booke of life, to thinke that the will of our maker, hath giuen all iudgement to our redeemer: if our friend be our Iudge, we will hope to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape the vigour of iudgement; if ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence come from our Sauiour, we may be aſſured of ſaluation. This made <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larion</hi> ſo often call to his ſoule. <hi>Exi ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea, exi. Goe out my ſoule, goe out willingly from the priſon of my bodie, thou haſt ſerued God theſe</hi> 70. <hi>yeares, neuer feare now, nor be loath to be going:</hi> whoſe life and death when good <hi>Saint Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rome</hi> read, he clapt vp his booke, ſaying <hi>Hillarion</hi> ſhall be the champion whom I will follow. This made <hi>Policarpus,</hi> that hee would neuer by flattering, nor threatning be drawne from the feruice of his Sauiour, liuing he neuer did him hurt, and dying he beleeued glory. This made that holy man on his death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, ſay. <hi>Neu vitam ſperno, nec mortem timeo, quia dominum bonum babeo: I nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loath my life, nor dread my death be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I haue ſo good a maiſten.</hi> This made
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:150657:54"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> deſire to be diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt, which is beſt of all. This makes the godly in the booke of the Reuelation, crie ſo earneſtly. <hi>Veni domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne Ieſu venicito: Come Lord Ieſu, come quickly:</hi> Euen ſo Amen, and let Amen ſay Amen. Come Lord Ieſu to make an end of a wicked, miſerable, vnconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, vncharitable word: Come Lord Ieſu to ſeale vp the kingdome of grace, which maketh thy Saints ſtay ſo long, and with long weary waiting crie, <hi>Qamdiu domine, How long Lord iuſt and true?</hi> Come Lord Ieſu to haſten thy Kingdome of glory, that we may the ſooner meet the King of glory, and be carried among the Angels into the place of glory, there to enioy the crowne of glory, with all the companie of heauen, to ſing glory to God on high. Al which he that made vs, for his Sonnes ſake grant vs, euen Chriſt the righteous: to whom with the Father, the Son, and the holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all praiſe, power, maieſtie, and dominion throughout all ages, now and euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:54"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150657:55" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
